<topics>
<!This Marks the start of Topic #1.>
<!Topic: Electric Chair.>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-electric-chair</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85032490/1887-04-17/ed-1/seq-10/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>DEATII Ef THE DYNAMO.
THE HANGMAN AND HIS GALLOWS
RELICS OF BARBARISM.
Dr. Smilhwick Discourses of a Moro Hu
mane Agent for tho Infliction of Cap
ital Punishment Description of Ills
Deadly Electric Chair.
Dr. A. P. Southwick, who is a member of
tho commission to ascertain the most
humano and practical method known to
modern science for carrying tho death sen
tence into effect in capital cases, is an enthu
siastic investigator, and since tho commis
sion was created by tho last legislature ho
has spent considerable time in making re
searches. "Do you believe in capital punishment,
doctor?" was asked.
"I believe tho death penalty is necessary,"
ho replied, "for there is a class of people, a
lower order of beings, to whom it is positive
ly necessary. I refer to peoplo who como
from a lino of murderers that is, men who
havo descended directly from families of
criminal proclivities. Tho man who walks
around ready to commit a willful, premedi
tated murder should die. He belongs to a
race that we want to wipo from tho face of
the earth. The laws are liberal enough, with
the various degrees of homicido and man
slaughter, to protect individuals who do it in
the heat of passion or under intense provo
cation." "And about women?"
"If the law i3 changed from hanging to
death by electricity then it should and
would bo made to include women as well as
men. Any discrimination between the sexes
would make the law unconstitutional."
""Would there b3 any objection to execut
ing women with electricity.'"
"No, sir; there would not. I think there
would no longer be tho samo prejudico that
thcro is now, because Imaging is a poor way
of inflicting the death penalty."
"How would you uso electricity?"
"Just seo here," said Dr. Southwick,
jumping up and .seating himself, in an arm
chair. "Tho condemned man cansifc natur
ally in a chair like this, placo his liands on
the metal arms and converse with those
around him. Tho metal plates would ba
connected with a powerful d3namo and at
tho proper moment somebody in another
room would press a button, closo tho current
and tho fatal shock would pass through tho
body of the subject. Tho chargo would go
straight through tho heart and lungs and
penetrate the system, death instantly result
ing. Tho expense of the apparatus with which
to execute by electricity ia this city would
bo about $150. Connection cculd bo made
with the electric light station, and tho ex
pense of an execution thereafter would bo of
littlo consequence. It would not cost any
more than a cigar to kill a condemned man
after that. It would not bo necessary to
maintain extensive and powerful machinery
in nil tho prisons, anil it would bo vastly
cheaper than hanging."
"You believe then in electricity?'
"Electricity Ls tho coming power. Death
is instantaneous and tho body i not defaced.
There is not tho morbidness of n hanging,
which is a relic cf barbarism. Just seo a
recent execution here Heman's I think it
was when tho hanged man breathed fifteen
minutes afteV the drop fell. If that is in
stantaneous death then I would rather havo
u lingering death."
"Have you considered jwisons as a means
of executing criminals''
"Prussic acid has been raggested, but
neither that nor garroting has met with any
favor. A few havo advocated tho guillotine,
but I thin!; it is a barbarous mode of causing
death. Hardly any one favors hanging in
preference to electricity, tho very system
being barbarous as are tlio method and
paraphernalia used.'
"Do you expect t!:at your plan wul be
adopted'"
"I sincerely hope i; w3L If it L adoptdl
by the coming legislarare otlxr slates will
undoubted!- adopi it, and I tiisk that
within two years it will bo adopted all over
the world- It wooll certainly L-j better
than obliterating the death penalty, and m
tho case of a woman there would b; much
less objection to its operation than there is
to hanging."
Dr. Soulhw'ci added that in England the
eamo quesuon had arisen, but no satisfactory
substitute for hanging had bsen suggested.
One of tho commissioners suggested that
various means bo adopted and the condemned
culprit 1x3 given his choice of deaths.
State Senator Daniel II. Meridian has
written a letter to the commission in which he
saj-s: "Tho principal objection to the present
inothod is that it Li primitive in its origin
and barbarous hi its effects. It lacks every
element of exactness and precision. It i3
absolute!' impossible to arrango a formula
as to the size of tho rope, tho longth of the
drop or the h"ft of the weight and the dis
tanco of its fall, as theso sc-vcral elements
must not only depend upon tho sizo and
weight but tho general buiid and make up ot
tho convict. Tho want of exactness in these
several elements sometimes leads to the muti
lation of tho bodv by severing the head; to
unnecessary and sevcro suffering by reason
of tho breaking of the rop?, nnd also to death
by sufTocal .en whero there has been an im
proper aijustment. All these things com
bine to luako hanging by the neck most
brutal.
"I am heartily in favor of the application
of electricity for tho purposes in question,
for the reason that it is simple, sure and
painless. 1 think that if the places of execu
tion wero limited to two in this state, say
ono at Auburn and ono at Sing Sing, the
two stato prisons, and that all convicts as
Foon as condemned to suffer tho death
penalty should bo confined in ono of those
two prisons (depending somewhat upon the
locality of tho trial), it would be a vast im
provement upon tho present method of hav
ing tho criminal confined in the county jail
till the daj- of execution."
Regarding tho machinery to Iw used
Senator llcl.lillan says: "Theso 'executions
could take place in tho jail proper, in a room
set apart for that purpose, with no appli
ances save that of a chair, with tuo nana
rest of each arm properly connected with
an electric machine, in which tho condemned
might bo seated and tho connection made by
strapping a hand to the hand rest on each
chair. There can bo no difficulty whatever
in procuring a current of electricity of suffi
cient strength to paralyze tho muscles of
tho heart by this method. Indeed, tho cur
rent that is used in this city for electric
lighting purposes is of sufficient strength to
absolutely dismember the body of nay human
being, but a current of electricity of suffi
cient strength to cause instantaneous death
by passing from hand to hand through the
heart wi'l not mark the body in tho least."</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86075267/1888-12-13/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text> Will Electrical Execu
tions Be Accomplished?
TlE LAST THING IN KILLING.
How Various Nations Do Their Criminals
to Death--New TYok State the Flrat
commeunty to Adapt the Newest Thing
in Capital PlUnihment. The subject of
putting murderers to death by electricity has
been agitated in the Empire state for more
than a year.
After mature deliberation it was concluded
that hanging would have to go.
Hanging has been the fashionable mode of
punishment for centuries, but a commission
*appointed by Governor Hill concluded that it
was too harrowing. They made a number
of experiments, and finally decided upon
electricity. A bill was passed by the legis
lature, but-no provision was made as to the
way the fluid was to be applied. This way of killing
off the refuse population will probably be
used in New York state hereafter. Three
ways of applying the fatal electricity were
proposed, but none of them answered the
purpose. One was passing the electri.
iots city from wrist to
wrist through the
body, another
was passing the
current from the
head to one of the
wrists, the third
Swas topassthecmu
rent completely
t through the prison.
S1 . etr's body from head
to foot.
c c m The objections to
A CURRENT IN THE BRAIn these methods were
that the prisoner might have convulsions.
It was desired, of course, to take the utmost
care of the prisoner. He was to die as pleas
antly as possible. Then the attendant under
this method might make a mistake and be
struck himself.
The commission finally concluded that the
best way would be to have the current pass
through the hoad from the top to the back of
the neck. One electrode is fitted to the top
of the prisoner's head, another placed in con
tact with the small of his back. The top
electrode connects with the positive pole, the
bottom with the negative pole. A leathern
rest holds the prisoner's head and bands
keep him from moving. The current, in go
ing from one electrode to another, does not
keep in a straight line, but spreads out and
goes through the entire brain. It resembles
somewhat a bundle of faggots tied at the two
ends and swelling out in the middle. The seat
of consciousness being in the brain, and the
headquarters for all the nerves being located
there, it is of course as plain as day that,
when an electro-motive force of 8, 30 volts
is applied, the prisoner is bound to die. The
great beauty of this system is that the pris
oners don't know it either.
Heroe we have a villain who is too bad to
stay around and commit murder any more.
Step up, ladies and gentlemen, and gazoon
the wayitisdone. Here we have astouttable
covered with rubber cloth and having holes
around its borders for binding. Prisoner,
come up here and lieon the table. Attendant,
bind the prisoner to the table. Here is an
electrode (the negative one) which comes up
through the table and touches the small of
the prisoner's back. Here we have a helmet,
to which the other electrode is joined, and
t helmet is put on the prisoner's head. The
Wtrode now touches the top of the prison
9~head, which has been moistened bywarm
ater. Prisoner, are you ready? Then, let
'cgo, Gallagher, and the thing is done. The
man is as dead as a
door nail.Now, however, the main object in
to get the prisoner out of the way as soon as
possible. In order to understand how quick
a man can die under the force of electricity,
let us consider first how fast a man can think.
Well, it takes just one-tenth of a second fora
nerve to communicate with the brain, ac
cording to Professor Hemholz Now Pro
fessor Tyndall estimates that an electric dis
charge occurs in one hundred thousandth of
a second, or ten thousand times more rapidly
than nerve transmission. So you see that it
it were possible a man would die by the
process described ten thousand times before
his nerves would have time to communicate
with his brain.
Last winter, for the purpose of ascertain
ing the effect of the electric light current on
the action of the heart, the thorax of a
chloroformed dog caught in Buffalo was
opened, so that the lungs and heart could be
seen in action by forcing respiration as in
conscious life. At the instant when the cur
rent passed through the heart it became a
mass of quivering flesh. It was noticed that
an attempt to breathe was made after the
current was passed through the dog. This
indicated that the brain had not lost its sus
ceptibility to impressions, and shows that in
execution the current should be passed
through the center. It should not be for
gotten, however, that the dog was from
utffalo. The commission couldheaveselected
no tougher subject than a Buffalo dog.
There can be no question, however, that
electricity is the thing to do the business.
HE LET HIMSELF DROP.
A Veracious Story of a Very Strange Ac
cident.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84025968/1890-08-07/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>"Electrocution" Not Wholly
a Success.
Two Shocks Required to Extinguish
the Last Spark of Life.
The Doomed Murderer Meets His Fate
with Wonderful Courage.
An Apnalllnef Scene When the Victim
Began to Return to Con
sciousness After the
First Shock.
Auburn, N. V., Aug. 6.—The trial
of a new means of taking htfman life,
while prompted by humane motives,
has resulted in a sickening spectacle
presented by a pinioned wretch, at
whose vital center was kept pounding
for some moments an alternating cur
rent of electricity which, though it ul
timately destroyed hia life, subjected
the criminal to a torture of whioh no
living being has knowledge, and which
none can describe. Im perfect registry
of the current pressure or faulty con
tact of the electrodes prevented in
stantaneous death. The reader may
gain some conception of the process of
this killing when the statement is
made that the person whose body
3hould be shaken into fragments could
not have suffered suoh pain as did
Kemmler, whose nerve cells and tis
sues were disintegrated not in a flash,
as designed, but by the relatively slow
strokes of the electric hammers upon
them. The shock was given at 0:43%, acd
was continued about 18 seconds. Two
minutes after the current was cut off
there was evidence of respiration. As
soon as possible the current waß re
turned and then cutoff. Again respir
ation was evident, after a f;w mo
ments. Saliva came from the mouth;
the chest heaved; there was wheezing
in tbe throat. The shock was again
put to tbe prisoner, who, the doctors
remarked, was unconscious from tbe
moment of the first shook. After a
short time smoke appeared at tbe
base; bis
FLESH WAS BURNING.;
Tne spectacle was most trying. The
man, the doctors said, suffered no
pain, however. The warden says the
voltage at first shock was 1800 volts,
which run down to a point not named.
After a third contact of four minutes
tbe man was declared dead. On examination it was found the sec
ond electrode burned through the skin
and into the flesh at the base of the
spire, making a scar nearly five inch
es iv diameter. Kemmler sat
down in the electric chair as qui
etly as though he was sitting down to
dinner. Warden Durston stood ou
the right and George Vieling, of Al
bany, ou the left. They began immed
iately to adjust the straps, the con
demned holding up his arms so as to
give them every assistance. When the
straps had been adjusted about the
body the arms were fastened down and
then the warden leaned over aud
parted Kemmler's feet so as to bring
the legs near the legs of the chair. When tho strap had been
adjusted the warden placed his band on
Kemmler's head aud held it against the
rubber cushion which ran over the back
of the chair. Kemmler's eyes were
turned to the other side of the room.
Before, they had followed the warden
in his movement about. Then the doom
ed mau made a fewremarks in a perfet
-1; clear, composed tone of voice: "Well
good luck" was one of them, and,
"Durston, see that things are all right"
was another, Vieling unfastened the
THURSDAY MORNING, AUGUST 7, 1890.
thumbscrew which held back tbe chair
in place and began to lower it so that
the rubber cap which had the saturated
sponge pressed againat the top of
Kemmler's head.
THE DOOMED MAN'S NEKVE.
The warden assisted in holding
Kemmler's head. Kemmler said, "Oh,
you had better press tbat down, part
ner, I guess; press that down." So the
head piece was undamped and pressed
further down. While it was beiDg
done Kemmler said, "Well, I want to
do the best I can; I can't do any better
than that."
Warden Durston took in his hand
the leather harness which was to
be adjusted to Kemmler's head.
It was a muzzle of broad leather
straps, which went across the fore
houd and chin. The top of the
strap pressed down against the
nose of Kemmler until it flattened it
down slightly over his face. Tho har
ness was put in place, Dr. Spitzka who
was atanding near the chair, aaid: God
bless you, Kemler,' and the condemned
man answered, "Thank you." Soft-
*
Death Chair. n. !
The dynamo in the machineshop was
running at good speed aud the voltme
ter on the wall showed a little more J
than 1000 volts. The warden turned to i
the assembled doctors and those im- ■
mediately around the execution chair
and said: "Do the doctors say it is all !
right?'' Hardly a minute bad elapsed
since the adjustment of tbe straps.
There was no time for Kemmler to have 1
weakened then, if his marvelous cour- 1
age had not been equal to the test of j
further delay, but there was no fear
that he would lose couraSe. He was as
firm in the chair aa before be entered !
the room.
THE FIRST SnOCK.At the warden's request Dr. Fell
stepped forward with a long syringe
in his hand and deftly wetted two
sponges which were at the electrodes,
one on top ol the head and the other at
the base of the spine. Tho water
which he put on them was impregnated
with salt. Dr. Spitzra answered the
warden's question with a shout of "All
right" which was echoed by others
about him. "Heady?" said Durston
again aud then "Good bye." He
stepped to tiie door and through the
opening said to some one in the next
room, but to whom will probably never
be known with certainty, "Everything
is ready." There was an almost im
mediate response and at HAS the elec
tric current was turned on.
There was a sudden oouvulsion of the
frame iv tbe chair. A spasm went
over Kemmler from head to foot. He
was confined by straps and springs
that held him so firmly that no limb or
other part of the body stirred more
than a small fraction of an inch
from its resting place. The twitching
tbat the muscles of the face underwent
gave it for a moment an expression
of pain, but no cry escaped from the
lips; which were free to move at will,
no sound came forth to suggest tbat
consciousness lasted more than tbe
infinitisimal fraction of a second—be
yond the calculation of human mind.
The body remained in a riged position
for seventeen seconds. The jury and
witnessses who remained seated up to
this moment came hurriedly forward
and surrounded the chair. There was
no movement of the body beyond the
first convulsion. It was not a pretty
sight, the man in his shirt sleeves
bound hand and foot, body and even
head, with the heavy' frame work
pressing down on top of the skull.
Dr. McDonald held a stop watch in
his hand and as the seconds flew by be,
noted their passage. Spitzka looked
at the stop watch and as the tenth
second expired he cried out "Stop!"
other voices cried "Stop." The ward
en turned to the doorway, called out
"Stop" to the man at the lever. A
quick movement of the arm and the
electric current was switched off.
There was a relaxation of the body in
the chair. "He's dead," said Spitzka
calmly. "Turn the current on instantly.
The man is not dead," "Turn on the
current."When the signal to
stop had come, the operator had
pressed the little button which gave
the sign to the engineer to stop
the dynamo. The dynamo was
almost at a standstill and the
volt metre registered an almost
imperceptible current. The opera
tor sprang to the button and
gave a sharp quick signal. There
was rapid response, but it was not
quick enough to anticipate tho signs
of reviving consciousness. As the group
or horror-stricken witnesses stood help
lessly by, all eyes were fixed on the
chair. Kemmler's lips began to drip
spittle and in a moment the chest be
gun to move and from the mouth came
heavy stertorous sounds, quickened
and increasing with respiration. There
was no voice but that of the warden
crying to the operator to turn ou the
current, and tbe wheezing sound, a
half groan, which forced itself past the
tightly closed lips, sounded through the
still chamber with ghastly distinctness.
Some of the witnesses turned away
from the sight.
ONE . FAINTED. it came with the same sudden
ness that marked tbe first shock which
passed through Kemmler's body. The
sound which horrified the listeners
about the chair was cut off sharply as
the body once more became rigid. The
slimy ooze still dropped from the mouth
aud ran slowly down the beard and on to
the gray vest. Twice wero there
wrenches of the body as the electri- I
cians in the next room threw the cur- j
rent on and off. There was no mistake I
this time about the killing. The dyna
mo was run up to the highest speed,
and again the full current of 2000 volts
was sent through the body. How long
this was kept in action no one knows.
To the excited group about tho chair it
seemed an interminable time. Dr.
Daniel, who thought he had an approx
imate idea of the time at least, said it
was four and a half minutes in all.
The warden's assistant who stood over
the dynamo, said on the record signal
the machinery was run only three aud
a half minuted all together.
No one was anxious to give the
signal to stop. AH dreaded the re
sponsibility of offering, to the man a
chance to revive or give again at least
those appearances of returning anima
tion which startled and sickened the
witnesses a few minutes before. As
the anxious group stood silently
watching the body, suddenly there I
rose from it
A WniTE VAPOR
Bearing with it the pungent and sick
ening odor of a body burning. Again
there were cries to stop the current and
again the warden sprang to the door
and gave a quick order to his assistan.
The current was stopped and again
there was a relaxation of the body.
Xo doubt this time the current had
done its work, if not well at least com
pletely. Dr. Fell who stood by the
side of the special correspondent of
the Associated Press, turned and said:
"Well, there is no doubt about one
thing, the mau never suffered untold
of pain." In atter consultations other
physicians expressed the same belief.
It was some mitigation of the horrors
of the situation to learn this,
butthe mitigation wa3 extremely slight
when it developed at another point
that some doctors disagreed very
materially.
DOCTORS AT VARIANCE.
Was Kemmler dead when the chest
moved and the lips gave forth those
strange ghastly sounds? Was be
breathing or was there an involuntary
and phenomenal movement of the chest
muscles? Some of the eminent experts
in attendance said to an Associated
Press correspondent while the body
was still warm in.tho chair that there
was no doubt these were signs of
returning animation; that respiiation.
for respiration they believed it to be,
was growing stronger, and tbat in time
if the current tjad not been turned on
again he would have revived. Others,
among them Dr. Spitzka, stated with
equal positiveness of couviction that
the first shock killed Kemmler instantly.
Doctors Daniels and Southwick, the
fathers of electrocide, believe that
Kemmler was dead, but they think the
current should have been continued
longer than 17 seconds, which was the
official time of the first contact. There
is no way in which a positive deter
mination of tbe question can be made.
It will always remain unsolved.<text/>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84025891/1895-09-07/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Then ahe was put on trial at Monticello,
found guilty of murder In the first decree
md sentenced to be killed by electricity.
3he was removed to Dannemora gagged
md bound on account of her violence.
Governor Flower commuted her sentence</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83016758/1899-06-01/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Sheriff of Mille Lacs County, Minnesota
The Death In the Chair.
The execution of Mrs. Martha M.
Place was a triumph of grisly justice.hat the ad
vancing temper of civilization is against
capital punishment and that capital
punishment will ultimately be modified
are not at all to the point Whatever
the penalty for murder may be, let it
be inflicted justly and impartially upon
offenders after due conviction, without
regard to other considerations than
those of justice to the innocent</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84028140/1901-10-29/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>With Brute Courage Czolgosz Met De
-th
In the Electric Chair.
Cowardice Quivered on His Lips, But Unsustained by Prayer or Hope of Eter
nity He Felt the Mask of Death Upon His Face and Passed to Oblivion,
Hated and Despised. F. Czolgosz, alias Fred Nieman, was
successfully electrocuted at Auburn
prison this morning. Ho took tho chair at 7:15 and In less
itlmo than It takes to tell it, tho deadly
current had paaHod through his body,
rubblnrr 'nmfeshla miserable existence
. with merciful and unerring swiftness.
Seated In tho chair, with the fatal
curroilt about to bo applied, Czolgosz,
V facing tho witnesses said;
"I shot the President becauso 1
thought It would benefit good work
ing people by ridding them of abom
inations. I am not sorry for my
crime."
During Oils time tho attendants wcro
busy strapping him to tho enalr. His
last words were: "I am heartily sorry
I did not see my father."
This was said after tho strap had
been drawn across his face, yet his
words were heard distinctly by all tho
witnesses in tho roomi Ho went to
his death unsupported by tho com
forting thought that ho had mado
pence with his God.
For Uie (lrst time In the history of
the prison a condemned man marched
to tlie fatal chair unaccorupnnicd by a
Spiritual advisor, Spiritual aid hod
been offered hUn, but ho scorned all
entreaties.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030193/1903-10-01/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>3 VAN WORMERS J
J
OlE IN THE CHAIR
IN FifTEEN MINUTES
The Brothers Are Electrocuted One
After the Other with Marvellous
i Speed Without a Hitch in the Triple
Tragedy Each Displaying Nerve
I Willis the Eldest Was the First tcTDie
Then Came Frederick the Youngest
I 1 and Burton Most Composed and De
l termined of All Was the Last QUICK WORK OF DEATH SHOCKS
WILLIS VAN WORMER entered the deathchamber at
113430 The current was turned into his body one
minute later He was dead at 1137
FRBDBRICK VAN WORMER entered the deathchamber at
11413O At 1142 the current was turned on He was
declared dead at 114330. The ceremony
1 of shocking them to death in the elecfrtfc chair consumed but thirty sec
I onds over fifteen minutes That length of time elapsed from the moment
when y1illis Van Wormer left his cell and started for the death chamber
until the physicians pronounced Burton Van Wormer the last of the trio
dead. Soon tho crowd was in the chamber of death and each ones seat was
pointed out to him as + ln a playhouee and each sat down to talk In
whispers with his neighbors With their eyes upon the stage and its grue
some 5ettgatbe chair with leathern straps and strange metal fittings
they had not long to wait before the curtain was rung up
The breaths of the witnesses could be heard at times as they sat there
and waited The noise of the opening of a lock made a rasping sound be
t hind the scenes and a catch came Into cacti ones throat There was the
f round of shuffling feet on the cement floor outside the door of death Now
L 1t was afthe threshold now Inside Some turned their heads to look most
4 stared straight ahead at the chair
WILLIS LED TO HIS DOOM
The priest with book In hand and murmuring llpg walked ahead Be
hind them came two strong guards and between them was Willis Van
Wormer He showed not a sign of fear
s Three paces brought the grim procession in front of the chair Other
ff guards were there ready to fasten the straps and the murderer fell into the
tt 1 jeai The States executioner lowered the electrode the hood with wet
brl sponges on it which makes the shock of the deadly current sure and the
1 mask dropped The hands that did these things worked quickly surely as
a w mane knitting They felt ona of the ma a legs where a little wire
with a wet sponge at the end of it was fixed They pressed it closer to tho
limb and then went over to a cabinet
There wna a vicious snakelike sound as if one should ejaculate some
thing that when spelled Bounded like Ss6spit
i The witnessed started Some of thorn heaved and shuddered like tho
form in the chair The death switch had been turned o t The room was as
a tomb In the middle pf a lovely night
THE FIRST OF THE KILLINGS</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84024827/1912-08-11/ed-1/seq-12/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>William Kemmlcr, a condemned
murderer, was put to death In the
electric chair In Auburn prison. Kern.
mler ttas the first victim to be legal
ly executed by electricity in tb Unit
ed States and his case was the sub
ject of wide discussion at the time. The action of New York In substitut
ing the electric chair for the gallows
has been found generally satisfact
ory and her example has been fol
lowed by Ohio, Virginia, South Caro
lina, Massachusetts, Kentucky auJ
New Jersey.
ijlnce the execution of Kemmler
there hae been 151 persona put to
death In the electric chair In New
York. The state prison authorities
estimate that It costs about J4000 per
individual to carry, out the capital
punishment mandate.  On the basis
of Oils estimate New York state haa
expended about JC3.000 for electro
cutions since that form of Inflicting
the death penalty was introduced.
Several times the electric chair at
Sing Sing has had two victims in
one day, and on one occasion a short
time ago three persons were put to
death within a period of twenty-four
hours. Rut never before has there
been such a wholesale execution of
death sentences Imposed on prison
ers In this state as is scheduled to
take place at Sing Sing next week.
Nino men are to die on the same
day, and In as rapid succession H3
they can be led to the death chair.
-:ix of the nine prospective victims
are the Italians who were convicted
of the atrocious murder of Mrs Mary
Hall at Croton Id Kit. Westchester
County, on Nov 9, 1911.</text>
	  </result></result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86061215/1915-07-31/ed-1/seq-8/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>He looked quickly at
the double row of witnesses, glanced
at the floor, swept with his eyes the
whitened walls of the room and then,
suddenly, as if coming to himself,
walked briskly over the rubber mat
and seated himself in the electric
chair. Behind Becker followed the
prison priests chanting the prayer of
death, which was repeated by the con
demned man.
"Jesus, ijtfary, Joseph, hkve mercy on
my soul," nervously spoke Becker as
deputy wardens stepped forward and
adjusted the electrodes. Hardly a
minhte elapsed before the electrode
was applied to the right leg, a slit
having been previously cut in the
trouser leg from the knee down. After
the electrode had been firmly adjusted
against a shaven spot on the back of
the condemned man's head, the state
executioner looked at Deputy Warden
Johnson, who surveyed the figure that
was ctlll mumbling the death prayer
in the chair. Johnson half turned his
head and the executioner jammed the
switch.
Three Shocks Given.
The first shock lasted a full minute
and the executioner said that it was
1,850 volts and ten aniperes in
strength. It came while Becker was
still commending his soul to his
niflknr.
I The two prison physicians stepped
forward to examine the collapsed flg
ure that sat supported in the death
chair by the thick black leather straps.
The stethoscope was applied to the
heart and Dr. Charles Farr, the prison
physician, pressed his finger against
the artery in the neck. There was
still a feeble fluttering of the heart.'
The physician stepped back from
the rubber mat and again the electric
current pulsed through the body. The
shock lasted seven seconds and the
current was then turned off. After 4
hasty examination Dr. Farr asked that
a third shock be given. This lasted
nve seconds. An examination that
took several minutes followed. Three
physicians among the witnesses then
made an examination and Dr.- Farr at
5:55 o'clock proriounced Becker dead.
Writes Last Statement.
During the night Becker penciled on
a piece of paper what he captioned
"My Dying Declaration." It was tak
en to the warden's office where two
copies were typewritten, which Becker
signed with his fountain pen in a bold
hand To Deputy Warden Johnson,
who bad charge of the execution in
place of Warden Thomas Mott Os
borne, who does not believe in the
death penalty, the one time police
lieutenant gave his fountain pen as a
gift. "It is the last thing that I have
to give away and I want you to have
it. I want you to give this statement
to the newspaper men."
Becker's message given out just be
fore he went to his death read:
"Gentlemen: I stand before you in
my full senses, knowing that no power
on -iarth can save me from the grave
that la to receive me. In the face of
that, in the teeth of those who con
demned me, and in the presence of my
God and your God I proclaim my ab
solute innocence of the foul crime for. he photograph was
not seen by the witnesses until the
prison" physician opened his coat as he
sat in the death chair.
Becker was put to death by the state
executioner whose name is unknown
to the public. This man succeeded
State Electrician Davis and he said he
would not take the job unless his name
wis kept secret. He lives in a little
town up-state and went about his
work briskly.
Becker's executioner said that in his
opinion the man had died instantly at
the first contact.
Negro Follows Becker.
An autopsy on the body of Becker
was performed, according to law, im
mediately after the execution. After
Becker's body had been removed from
the electric chair, Samuel Haynes, a
nefgro murderer, was brought into the
execution room and electrocuted. One
of Becker's last requests to Warden
Osborne was that''he be put to death
before Haynes. Herman Rosenthal, the gambler for
whose murder Charles Becker was sen
tenced to die in the electric chair, was
shot to death by hired gunmen in the
early morning of July 16, 1912, in front
of the Hotel Metropole on Forty-third
street, a few stepB from Broadway. A verdict of guilty of first degree
murder was returned at midnight
October 24, 1912, after the jury had
deliberated seven hours and fifty-seven
minutes. Becker was sentenced six
days later to die 1 the electric chair
during the week of December 9, 1912.
Within less than amonth the four gun
men were placed on trial as the actual
slayers, found guilty and sent to the
death house.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045389/1916-03-05/ed-1/seq-48/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>the electric chair was sub
stituted for the old fashioned
gallows in New York it was be
cause it was believed that electrocution
was painless. But just what were the
sensations of death in the electric chair
scientists were unable to say, because
no electrocuted victim came back to life
to tell tliern.
It was assumed that the shock of the
powerful current would instantly render
the condemned man unconscious. But
the unpleasant feature of m^st electro
cutions has been the necessity of re
penting the shock several times. This
was not foreseen
Experience in ilie death chamber has
shown that the electric current does
not usually destroy life at the tirst shock.
Evidences of pulsating life compel the
executioner to turn on the current asain
and yet again. This distressing failure
of the electric charge to instantly end
life has caused much speculation among
scientists and humanitarians.
Does the first shock end the conscious
ness of the condemned man?
Or is the victim siiil conscious?hover
ing between death and life, does themau
In the chair realize what is going on?
What, if any, was the agony of the
ti rs ? shock?
What were the agonies of the victim
during the moments elapsing between
tiie tirst shock and the second impact of
the current? Was he entirely uncon
scious, partly conscious or fully conscious
of the horrors of the situation which the
law never meant to be inflicted on him?
And if the tirst shock of the current
benumbed the condemned man's brain,
did returning consciousness bring with it
tortures of bodily misery which have
never been known or suspected? an eloctrocuted vic
tim?with ilie very import air addition
that Tonious had coin" back to life and
full consc.ensue* and wa? abb to nippiy
the answers to t ie mysteries which liav
heretofore always been burled with the
remains of the electrocuted murderers
Pressed 'or information on all the as
pects of : i- :? markab'.e experience,
Tonious said:
"Dying wa- quick and without much
pain. Coming back to life was slow and
very painful.
"When 1 stared to hacK out of the
elevator." Toniou continued, " I recall
stepping "ti the wire. I could feel it
under my fe>ot. Then ! felt a teirible
jolt on thf- back of my head It felt as
if some one had struck me there with a
club. 1 remember having cried out, but
my voice seemed to trail off in tin* nis
taace. It felt as if a bomb bad been
inserted in rny skull and as if it bad
exploded and blown off the top of my
head.
. "Then it aeemed as if a million needles
nnd pins were shooting through my body.
They pricked all at the same time. The
top of my head seemed to rise. 1 felt
the ground giving way under my feet as
?if I were on the brink of a precipice the
edge of which had crumbled under me.
I felt myself falling. There was nothing
to support me. 1 realized that no part of
mv body was moving of its own accord,
but the whole of me kept falling. All this
appeared to be in a short space of titer,
probably no more than a few seconds,
ami then finally l felt as if i were float
ing in space. 1 couldn't see. hear, smell
or feel anything, and then suddenly oil
was a blank. I just couldn't think or re
member anything.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030431/1919-08-03/ed-1/seq-27/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Standing between a condemned mur
derer facing death in the electric
chair and his freedom, the watchman's
task in the condemned cells Is a tick
lish one. for the first electric
execution arrived at the prison.
New Tork State had just passed a
law substituting the electric chair for
the hangman's noose. There had
never been an electric execution and
everybody was prospecting as to who
would be the first person electrocuted
and'whether he would bo killed with
out conscious suffering or tortured to
death. f
On October 30, 1889, Warden Brush
received Charles McElvalne, aged
twenty, the first person sentenced to
the electric-' chair., He had- slain
Christian Lucca In Brooklyn. There
had been no deathhouse built then.
So"McElvalne was placed' in a cell on
the upper floor of tho hospital building
end kepA In 'solitary conflneme'nt;-' On
December 5, 1889, work of building tho
deathhouse was begun. It was to be,
virtually, a prison within a prison.
Derrenbachcr saw Thomas Palllster,
a prisoner, helping to build it. By
an odd turn of events, this same pris
oner was later convicted of murder
and lodged, two years later, in the
prison death cells himself. He was
never executed. He cheated the chair
by escaping,
Deathhouse Snon Crowded.
Soon as the deathhouse was finished
McKlvalne became Its first occupant.
Derrenbacher was his first guard
there. Ho would keep watch over the
condemned murderer eleven hours a
day. McElvalne hud not the exclusive
use of' the deathhouse long. On New
Year's day Sheheok Julglgo, a Japa
nese, was received from Manhattan
for killing Seaman Coutaln, a Japanese
sailor.  Warden Brush wished to
test the killing capacity of the new
contrivance. So on Nov. 20, 1890, a
horse was taken from the prison stable
and fastened to the death chair In a
room adjoining tho condemned colls,
where Derrenbacher was on duty. The
keepers fastened a hood, over the
horse's head, as they do now over tho
cranium of a murderer, and tied the
steed fast to the chair.
As the current was turned on a fuse
blew out and the horso got only a part
of the shock that was meant for It. It
made a weird shrieking noise and
kicked the wall furiously.
The commotion Btartled Slocum.
"What's that?" asked the wife slayer.
Derrenbacher knew they were testing
the chair, but would not add to
Slocum's mental torture. "It s only a
horse kicking," replied the keeper,
Little did Slocum realize they were
trying out tho chair to use on the
deathhouse Inmates. Or that destiny
intended that he should be the first
person ever to sit in it. Warden Brown had pledged all who
would have access to the condemned
cells and the death chamber to se
crecy. Newspaper reporters were not
only forbidden to see the execution
(they hod been allowed to witness
hangings) but the warden put out
armed sentries and kept them off the
prison property entirely.  Brown arranged a code of
signals to let reporters and others
know when each of the four prisoners
to be electrocuted was dead. He se
lected a white (lag for Sloqum, a blue
flag for Smller, a black flag for Wood
and a red flag for Julglgo. When each
man was dead his flag was to go up
the halyards on the root of the war
den's residence. So the thousands
awaiting outside the prison -riveted
their gaze on the flagpole. The
electrodes were jammed down on his
head, the mask drawn over his face,
and Dr. Carlos Macdonald, the alienist,
signalled the executioner to pull the
switch. Tho current shot on, Slocum
lunged forward and tugged at the
straps. Tho first shock had left him
unconscious, but another was given
him to make death certatn. The mob .realized the new
experimental' electric device had done
its grejsome work and that Slocum
was tho first to go.
Derrenbacher then got Smller ready,
bid him good-by and saw htm led oil
to the deadly contrivance Next he
opened the cell door for Wood, shook
his hand and bid him good-by. Final
ly Derrenbacher unlocked the cell of
Julglgo. Because tho Japanese was a
powerful and brutal man tho prison
authorities feared trouble from him.
So they left him until tho last. Julglgo,
however, surprised them. He nodded
good-by to 'Derrenbacher, walked erect
to the chair and went to his death as
stolid as an ox.
Derrenbacher remembers how brave
ly McElvalne faced the chair. "He
walked upright and quickly," said the
keeper, "sat squarely down in the chair
and said: 'Let'er got " Mrs. Buchanan rat, hysterical, In
Warden Sage's residence whilo her son
was being killed In the death chamber.
Mnrle nurberl Saved From Death,
Meserole recalls tho" occasion when
he was stationed over Marie Barberl,
the first woman ever sentenced id the
electric chair. In the dingy room was a murderer's
body and outside the door was the
carcass ot another horse killed In the
electric chair Cor experimental tests,
Van Wart opened the cell for Martin
Thorn on his execution .day. Thorn!
was the slayer of William Gulden
suppe, whom he murdered In New
York in cahoots with Mrs, Nack, This
crime .became famous because the only
clue to the perpetrators, when the
-3;
History of Electric
Chair, Desperate
Breaks for Free
dom, Murders
Within Prison and
Attemftts at Sui
cide Figure in
Reminiscences
body was found cut up, was a shirt
button. The manufacturer of the but
ton and the sale of the shirt was
traced, the body Identified as Gulden
suppe's and Thorn and the woman ar
rosted. Thorn was electrocuted Aug.
1, 1898." "He walked like a major,"
said Van Wart.
</text>
	  </result>
	  <!STARTING HERE IS TOPIC 1, 10 EXTRA DOCS.>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85066387/1901-10-29/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The electrical, machine is ready for its
work ; ; Auburn prison is carefully,
guarded, the city Is in its normal' calm,'
and .there seem to be.no circumstances
standing in the way of a successful and
expeditious execution of the law.
Last Two Interviews.
Czolgosz will have paid tribute with his
life to the law, as the murderer, of Presi
dent William McKinley, by 7:15 o'clock to
morrow morning^, and Tunless he under
goes a great change 'of heart and
strength in the few hours of life. left to
him, he will go to the electric chair un
confessed and unrepentant. ASSASSIN CZOLGOSZ PAYS DEATH PENALTY IN THE ELECTRIC CHAIR AT AUBURN PRISON
AUBURN, N. Y., Oct. 29.— At 7:13 o'clock this morning Leon F. Czolgosz, the anarchist who fatally shot President William McKinley at the Buffalo
Exposition on September 6, was electrocuted. The assassin went to the electric chair unrepentant and unconfessed.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85058130/1898-08-02/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THORN PUT TO DEATH
Murderer Pays the Penalty For His
Atrocious Crime
KILLED BY ELECTRICITY
LIFE WAS EXTINCT IN LESS
THAN A MINUTE. I
Walked to the Death Chair Re
peating Prayers After the Priest
Horrible Crime For Which He
Was Executed
New York Aug 1 Martin Thorn
was put to death in the prison at Sing
Sing at 1117 this morning for the
murder of William Guldensuppe. his only dread was the wait from the
time he awoke until he was summoned
to the chair The condemned man re
ceived the last sacraments of the
Roman Catholic church
When summoned to the execution
chair Thorn showed no emotion.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86071197/1901-09-27/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>the crowd slowlv filed out of the roons
and the court adjourned ut 2 20 p m
Tho death warrant signed by Justlco
White Is addiessed to the agent and war
den of Auburn Male prison and directs
him to execute the sentence of tho court
within the walls of tho prison on soma
duv dining the week beginning OcttSr M
next bj canning to pass through tho
body of the sild Ienn r Czolgosz a eur
rent of eleclrliltv sufficient to cause death
and that the application of the said cm
lent of eleclrleltj be continued until be
the said Leon F Czolgosz bo dead</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85042243/1935-02-14/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>New Jersey Death House Awaits Convicted Hauptmann 
When a prisoner convicted of murder in New Jersey is condemned to death, It Is in this windowless,
fortress-like building in the confines of the state penitentiary at Trenton that he must await execution.
The death cells concealed by the blind walls are almost as austere, nothing being provided that would
enable the prisoner to cheat the grim electric chair (pictured at right) housed in a small room at the
end of the cell corridor. Bruno Richard Haupt
mann woke from a fitful sleep Thursday, a man condemned to
die in the electric chair for the murder of Baby Charles A
Lindbergh, Jr.
Edward J. Reilly, chief of his defense counsel, character
ized the conviction and sentence a “miscarriage of justice.” He
and his three associates prepared to ask a stay of sentence and
start the machinery of appeal. A few strides away stood Haupt
mann, jaw set, face so pale and hag
gard it was ghastly in the electric
light. Sharply erect, he tottered
slightly as he heard the foremans
words.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86063811/1936-04-04/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Kruno Richard linuptmaiin convicted kidnap-murderer of
Chas. A. Lindbergh, Jr., wont to his d^ath la^t night-in the electric
chair of New Jersey maintaining grim rilence after protesting hi? in
nocence in the final days of the hectic politico-legal light that, pre
ceded his execution. Bruno Richard Hauptmann's
last cry of "innocent" before he
walked to the electric chair last
night retarded the Lindbergh case
as the most, controversial!) my
stery of the: ceutury. Hauptmann
died calmly, almost indifferently,
with his thin lip.s sealed against
the slightest hint of confession. The slate of New Jersey,
which sper.t $1,200,000 to capture
and convict Bruno Richard Haupt
mann, executed thim last night
with a penny s worth of electric
ity.
Hauptmann entered the door of
the death house at i-tate prison at
8:41 p. m.
The first of three shocks went
through his body at 8:42 1-2.
Physicians pronounced him dead
at 8:47 1-2 p. in.
Before his body ever hung loose
and heavy against the straps of
the electric chair, officials collect
ed from witnesses a dozen affi
davits, swearing that Hauptmann
had died in the place, time and
manner prescribed by law. Then
they closed their four-year file on
the murder of Charles A. Lind
bergh, Jr.
Hauptmann died without con
fessing.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov./lccn/sn83045487/1912-01-09/ed-1/seq-28/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>RICHESON SENTENCED TO
ELECTRIC CHAIR
Boston, Mass., Jan. 9. The
shadow of the electric chair
hangst his evening over Rev. C.
V-T. Richeson, murderer of Avis
Linnell, his sweetheart whom he
betrayed under promise of mar
riage. His only hope of escape
from ignominious death lies in
the hands of the nine men com
posing the governor's council, the
court of last resort for con
demned men in this state.
While they are epected'eventu
ally to save the minister murder
er from the chair, the decision
will be uncertain for some time.
Four members of thecouncil are
known to oppose capital punish
ment. .</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov./lccn/sn86069309/1910-09-28/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Work On The Death Chair
The Frankfort correspondent of the
CourierJournal writes his paper as fol
lows
Although it is expected that the
chair may not be used for many mouths
the work for installing the death chair
at the Eddyville penitentiary is going
on steadily the Prison Commission
taking no chances on being caught nap
ping The chair will be ready in a few
weeks and any condemned man who is
to die in the chair will be put to death
at Eddyville Is considered the most ap
proved manner The electrocution law
became effective on June 14 dud Ifa
crime is committed after that time for
which the death penalty is imposed by
the Judge and jury turf condemned man
will be electrocuted But the electro
cutioulaw applies only to crimes cow
initted after the law became effective
As there is always delay in Inflicting
the death sentence on account of ap
peals and the usual legal delays it is
hardly probable that an electrocution
will take place for some mouths yet
Only a few muders where the death
penalty is likely to be imposed have
been committeed in Kentucky since the
new law became effective and the death
penalty has not been returned by any
jury since that time
Many persons have wondered why
the death chair was not located at
Frankfort The reason is that the Frank
fort penitentiary soon will cease to be
called a peniteutary but will be a re
formatory and it WAS considered hard
ly I proper to inflict the death penalty in
a reformatory Another objection was
that there are two many sightseers in
Frankfort and they would all want to
go to the penitentiary and Bee the death
chair So the Prison Commission did
not hesitate long about where they
would locate the place for putting to
death of condemned men</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov./lccn/sn83045293/1913-03-28/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The
laat of the old feud bands was
wiped out today when Floyd and
Claude Allen, father and son,
leaders of the most notorious
bands that ever terrorized the
mountain regions, were executed
in the electric chair.
Hoping against hope to the last
minute that their death sentences
would he commuted to life imprison
ment, the two men went to the death
chair with fleeting hopes that before
the thousands of volts of electricity
would be sent through their bodies
they would be given a chance to live. Supt.
Wood of Richmond jail set the hour
of their execution at 1 o’clock.
Enter Death Chamber.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov./lccn/sn85042303/1915-07-08/ed-1/seq-5/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>TWO PRISONERS SENTENCED TO
DIE WILL GET REPRIEVE UNTIL
DEATH CHAIR SHALL BE IN
STALLED. Oklahoma City, July 7. -Death in
tlie electric chair has been the sen
tence for several persons convicted
of capital offenses in Oklahoma during
the last two years, but up to this time
none have so suffered. The last pre
ceding admiiiislrat ion was opporcd to
capital pii.ii.Mimcnt and there was no
electric chair in the penitentiary.
This administration is alleged not to
be opposed to the death penalty and
there are two death sentences await
ing arrival of the date sent for execu
tion. These dates will be in advance
of the readiness of the electric chair,
however, and (loveruor Williams has
said that he will reprieve the prison
ers In order that they may he execut-
! ed in the new chair when tiie state
i
j board of affairs shall have that instru
ment of retributive justice ready.
Tiie state board of public affairs
undertook several months ago when
tlie appropriation for a death chair
became available to build the chair nt
the MeAlester prison. It was under
stood that the work was making rapid
progress until last week, when tho
board rcelvcd bids for supplying the
complicated electrical apparatus that
makes Ihe chair n death chair. Now,
It is understood, the chair will not be
ready for the executions set for July
:I0 and Aug G, and that they will be de
layed. It. C. Moorehead, a negro who killed
Clifford Carrion at Snyder, February
7, 1915, was sentenced to die July 3D.
Henry Booklan of Mcintosh County
was sentenced to die in the chair Aug.
C. So far neither case has been ap
pealed to the criminal court of up
peuls, and the death penalty will prob
ably be exacted when the electric
chair shall be ready.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov./lccn/sn86092356/1904-10-07/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>"DUTCH" FISHER ELECTROCUTED
Special to The Oil Review.
Columbus. O.. Oct. 7. ? "Dutch"
Fisher was electrocuted in the
State prison in this city at 12 :03
this morning. The condemned
man seated himself in the death
chair smiling- and with all the
nonchalance of a man sitting down
to a good dinner. The execution
was wholly devoid of any sensa
tional features. Fisher died refus
ing to give his real name even
to his own attorney and declared
with almost his last breath that
"Walter Crosby, now serving a life
sentence for complicity in the
murder, was entirely innocent of
the crime.</text>
	  </result>
    </results>	
  </topic>
  <!This Marks the start of Topic #2.>
  <!Topic: Brooklyn Bridge.>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-brooklyn-bridge</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1883-05-23/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<!The text on this page is beyond incomprehensible. I would add more but I cant understand it.>
	<text>The Central I..thor Unions of New-York ami
Brooklyn have Issued an address to the working
people of tho two cities denouncing the trustees
for deciding to open thc bruise on the Queen'i
birthday and asking " all good mon and woman io
both cities to remember this latest insult of tho
would-be aristocratic element in oar midst." and
not to assist by their presence at, the opening of tbe
bridge.
The dome of tho New-York Post Office will be
lighted liv electricity to-morrow evouiiui.
Persons who Wish to illuminate tneir houses or
places of business may timi lt desirable to use the
following recipe for the Hentral liu'tit. which ia
prrlectly harmless and haras with it linliant white
(lame: nitre, one nontid: sulphur, five ounces;
-ii I i.inirei of antimony, two snd a half ounces; iub
together and ligiit.iu small quantities with a match
VISITORS FROM BUFFALO.
Bltpalo, May 22.?Tbe Delaware, Lack*
awsana sad western EUilroad Company has extended
Invitationa to tbe Mayor, mern he rs or the Coasaoa Cooav
eil, heads of iii partim-nts ami representative tmslaesa
mea of tale etty to sttend toe speolns of the Brooklyn
Bridge. A special train will leave this elty Wednesday. 
The whole party will prol
ipeningol the Hrooklyn Bridge. At the centroid tbe bridge rocksta ami
bouiha will bs dis. harton! in tl 1.1 ways and lira
balloons will Its seut ip I rom the foot-bridge.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030272/1883-05-24/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>he Brooklyn llridgc
i
On the 3 of January 1870 the wOk of
I preparing for tlio foundation of the towel In
Brooklyn was begun and the stouo tablet
I close to tho top of that mighty pile bal the
date of 187J A similar tablet lu tho dice of
the New York pier bears the same date al
though It was not finished and ready for the
I I cable until a year Inter A person who
11 never had built such a bridge would naturally
i ural suppose that the cnbles rondo up of
thousands of fine steel wIre would bo put to
gether aud then hoisted to their proper place
on top of the lower But this was not tho
way On Aug 14 1B7C the end of a small
wire was fastened to 1 scow on one side of
tho river and carried across to the other
I side where It was hauled up aloft so that
it cleared the masts of ships and then other
wlrea and ropes wero passed back and
I forth by means of the llret until a footway
was built and the machines made ready to
stretch tho cable wires across And
6 the great cables grew la tho air
l until they reached their present size
Then tho Iron roidwav were fastened to
a them two carriage ways two railroad tracks
nd a footpath and today a little moro
than thirteen years from tho time of Its
beginning Mayor Low will enter the bridge
from the Brooklyn end with a crowd of his
Drokln
I flow citizens and wait at tho Brooklyn
station to receive the Mayor of Now York
1 who will come across with a crowd of his
fellow cltbeus Including the President of
the United States. Then after the party
have reached Brooklyn the President will
haveachaucoto hear tho presentation speech
by Mr WILLIAM I C KixastEY. The present truffle his been uccommo
i dated by the ferryboats and the bridge
will scarcely improve tho facility for tic
I crossing of teams to such 1 degree that 1
I much greater quantity of goods will at one
bo sent over from Brooklyn to Now York or
i from Now Yoik to liiooUlyn Possibly sonic
jieoplo doing business in tho lower part of New
York but who have bo seriously objected t
crossing the ilvor twice a day in the ferry
boats that they have lived Inferior accom
mulatlon in Hurlom may now go to live II
Brooklyn but the number Is not likely to ue
large Wo think theieforo that the bridge Is I
not destined to bare any startling Immediate
foci on the business relations of tho two
cities CUent causes act gradually. But what a monument the bridge Is i The
long slope leading from tho entrance past
the anchorage with the cables eprlnglng out
if t tho Iron structure up to tho top of the
iilere to bo mot again on tho other side
hero they descend to tho roadbed tho
grand Gothic arches over tho passages
thorough HID towers may well strike one
with awe and admiration at tho ability of
Inn t pile up such an edifice Whether one
lands upon It or looks at It from a
Istauce or passes underneath It presents
the name air of majestic grandeur and lude
tructlbli solidity that must cause It to bo
forever counted tho most Imposing
01 over cOlutCd among moetlUposlng
buildIngs that have ever been raised And
when one thinks of tho dally uso this vast
structure will bo to thousands of people It
assume a character whlchcaubcs it to stand
out distinct from all other works of equal
mgnltude May tho bridge lat forever uud
reflect eternal honor on lu builders I
Mr Chandler Armadn
Every citizen of New York should go down
to the Battery today and view the fleet of
menofwar tent by the Secretary of tho
Nay to assist In the bridge enlebrntlon It
s I rare spectacle Five American war ships
are not often seen together riding at anchor
In this harbor. That Is about twothlidsas much us has
been spent in building tho bridge that will
stand for centuries Oo and gaze upon these
Itobeboulau ships of war before they rot or
sink. n Broad
way and tho story about tlio throats because
of tho opening of tho Brooklyn Bridge on
Quoon YICTOHUH birthday I would not b
surprising I thoy should think that times must
be oven more dreadful hero than thoy sro In
Ireland Itself And yet what a morrytcoround
wo aro having In Now iork
All the people of Brooklyn should pay a
visit to Now York city today mid take a look
at the Ooeoratlons of THE HUN ofllco No doubt
a Mint multitude of Now Yorkers will utaa upon
theta with uatrlotiaand artistic delight and I
will bo hard work for them to refrain from
cryIng. Ladles ay hera too are ladles of Brooklyn and
New York It Is n festive tpcctaco truly But
tint olilur ItotDLiMi whoplaniiHl the bridge Is I
toll and tho younger HOKIIIINO who built It
Is I disabled How the stout old German to
whom wu owe hO I much as tho designer of the
brldirn would have rejoiced toduy had ho
lived to this. I appears that the trim moanIng of thin Stock
xeliantoromalnlinopen today Into bo HOII uh t
In thou fact that thou Brooklyn Bridge author
Ins havo ignored Wall street In their Invas
ions to tho pnguunt Thoro can bo no doubt
hat thou Now York Htock llxchunke ns I body
Iq ono of tho richest most liberal und most In
fluential corporations</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1883-05-24/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<!The text on this page is also incomprehensible.>
	<text>Tho formal opening of the New-York and
Brooklyn Bridge will take place to-day. Tha
President, Governor Cleveland and other prom?
inent guests will bo escorted over tko struc?
ture by tho 7th Regiment to the Brooklyn
terminus, whore tho opening exercises will bo
held. Tlio station building at the Brooklyu end of the
llrulge has bsaa Aaoaraiail lavishly with festooned
lingi, the coats ot arms of all tho States between
Ihe vvniiti)ws, and nina velvet banginga with gold
embroidery overhead. Tho railroad tracks have
been temporarily .loured over, aud ou thou upward
of -l,ooo th.tils have been pla, ed. Tho sis-akers*
platform is near the no them end. tow arti tins city,
and ibo building ia open at Lotti ends. A place
moir) utiiittod foi ora'ory it would not he possible
to provide. It nsssabtss as much as |tu>i.-.il,lo a
section af a tunnel BO feet wide, open at butti ends,
and nearly lill feet long. Tho voice oven of the
moat powerful speaker will ho lost ami inaudible
except Wittiiu a very In w feet"! bun. To most of
thosaaithiu the bttlldlng the spsaaars will simply
ur pear to Lo gong through the motton - ut deliver
rig orations and Beatons ut tlie New Vork cud of
tba Bridge will Lave .ts good acfeaaoaaf I.e..nug
what ie said ea asset af those who hors t hs win io
tn Leta of a lunsMoii to tho bailding. Tbe ouly way
to hoar the -.ped Ins will ho through thc nowa
psjanta.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1883-05-31/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<!I know some articles have terrible transcripts, but the ones for the brooklyn-bridge have to be the worst ever.>
	<text>Great excite?
ment prevailed in the city and Brooklyn,
aud exaggerated stories of the' calamity were
apread. Tkiiuxe reporters last night
vi-itcd prominent Bridge Trustees
New-York and Brooklyn and other offi?
cials, and obtained their opinions ns
to the cause of the accident and the
means that must be taken to prevent similar
occurrences in the future. The accident is
attributed largely to the iuelliciency of tiie po?
lice system and the police force of the Bridge. yesterday the great Bridge was the most
popular thoroughfare in the city.  Bridge bad fallen down
and l.DoO people had lost their lives. n New-York.
Her host, whose nsme could not be learned, with hts
littleiboy, was accompanying her across the Bridge
when the crowd lugan to press upon.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82014381/1883-05-31/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>New Yobk. May SOtb.— terrible acci
dent occurred '", on , the Brooklyn bridge at
half-past 4 o'clock. The bridge waa crowded
to its utmost opacity at that hour. On the
platform on the New York tower the jam be
came S3 great that many persons fainted. A
cry of distress was raised, and a dreadful
struggle began between the panic-stricken
crowds comisK.rrom the east and west. A
number were, it is reported, crushed to death.
In the end the crowd cominer from the Brook
lyn side prevailed, and rushed toward tha
New York anchoring, trampirg down every
thing in its way. Mer, women and children
were ■ trodden under foot, and falling
down ; the Btfpj ieadiuß to the tower
platform, were buried • under a mass
of ■- gfrufrglfng humanity muny feet
high. As scon as tbe news cf tbe disaster was
conveyed to the New York station by the
oust of the panic-stricken crowd, the police
were called atd the bridge was closed. The
work cf removing the crushed ar.d wounded
then began. A number were taken to the
City Hall police station, acd others to the
Chambsrs-street Hospital." The police report
at least ten or fifteen killed, but as yet it is
impossible to say whom or how many. Of
the seven wounded who ere in the City Hall
station, one, B. Reychers, a cigannaker of
No. 335 Deianey street, is now . dying. The
excitement at the entrance to tha bridge is
intense.  It was
a remorseless, fearful, BtupMiorce, that held
its victims as immovable as the stone foun
dation of the bridge . itself. The stoppage
lasted nearly an hour, daring which time
scores of people fainted. To relieve the jam
the bridge officials removed some cf tbe iron
pilirg a few feet from the stairway on the
New York side, when of course there was an
immediate, rush to that point, and a large
number fell, helter-skelter, heels over head,
down on the jagged, gravelly road beneath, a
mass of braised and discolored human flesh.
Scores were trampled upon and instantly
killed. I went on the 1 bridge," said Charles
Bright, of 59 Third street, Brooklyn, "at
about 4 o'clock, and :as I was , approaching
the river span I found myself unable to move
either backward or forward. '■; Women and
children \ commenced ecreaming. Hundreds
of men climbed with great difficulty into the
beams musing over the rails, and made their
way to the carriage way. Many let them
selves drop through the bo wen beams; and
were caught by those beneath. A cumber of
women escaped in this way. : The police and
others helped pull out the • dead and ' dyin£,
and they were laid ■ on the roadway until the
ambulances came. The shrieks of the chil
dren in the pathway were blood-curdling.
They .; cried, ' Help ! help ! : Save ; "me, j for
God's sake ! ' but where we were we could do
nothing. the Brooklyn bridge this
afternoon. ; A . panic followed, and at least
fourteen .-• people ' were • killed and ■ many
wounded. ; The crush began shortly before 4
o'clock, at which hour there ware thousands of
people on the bridge, most cf them coming from
Brooklyn. The air was clear and brisk, and
tha ' people were ; rapidly walking.' . As the
crowd approached, the short flight of steps
those ■; in front pushed back, for fear they
would be precipitated over the steps, a dis
tance of -about six feet. ; These people, in
dra\. ' "V : fro the : itepn, ; made the
nucleus t '■* the thousands behind
them v pusteu ;. .-•* , unheeding. Almost in
stantly the people began to shout, '• Stand
back!" and : "Give us room!" Meanwhile
tho crowd from New York, which was at the
foot of the steps," got blocked. The men at
the head cf the New York crowd fought
their way back, leaving a clear spaca at lha
foot of tho steps. The crowding and shout
ing from ~ • the Brooklyn side in
creased. It was utterly inexplicable. The
people in the advance guard cf th 9 Brooklyn
crowd were pushed toward th.3 steps. They
seemed to have a horror of . going over the
steps, although the right is only five to six
feet. : They locked arms and poshed furi
ously back sgaiast the thousands coming
steadily over from Brooklyn. In a few min
utes there was a slow yielding to the frightful
pressure from behind, and tha frcnV of the
crowd was forced nearer and nearer to the
edge of the step?, where ;
CHILDREN WERE SCHEAMIXG FOR HELP
And shouting confusedly. Umbrellas, par
cels &nd canes were thrown over the rails by
people who needed their hands to fight their
way out of the desperate crowd. :At last,
with a siEgle desperate shriek, that cut
through the clamor cf a thou?aad voice?, a
young girl, who lost her footing on tha peril
ous edge, fell headlong. She struck the
hatchway at thj foot of the steps, sad lay for
a moment. Shs raised hereelf on her hand?,
and would have got up, but fa another mo
ment she was buried four deep under the
bodies of others who fell over the steps after
her. She was dead when they got her cut,
more than half an hour ' afterward. Men
sprang :pjn tLo rails at the Ads and waved
the crowds back from tho New York and
Brooklyn tide?, bat . the people continued to
crowd on toward the steps. No police were in
sight, and the excitecent grew wort c. Men
in tbe crowd lifted their children above their
heads to save them from the crush.. People
were still paying their pennies at both gates
and cqueezing in. At last the pet pie at the
New York end of the bridge understood what
was happening. The gates were closed, and
word was sent to Brooklyn to cloee the gates
there. Messengers were sent to the police
station in Oak street, but before any outside
help came the bridge police, assisted by citi
zens, impressed two grocers' wagons into am
bulance Bervic9, They were
LOADED DP WITH THE DEAD ASD DTISG,
And driven off the bridge, followed bycrcwds
of distracted men and women.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86069871/1883-06-05/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>BROOKLYN BRIDGE.
Formal Opening to th Public of the
Great Structure Connecting: the Cities of
jfew York and Brooklyn The Two Cltiea
jn Gala Attire A Grand Pyrotechnic
Display.
New York, May 25.
Although the day opened cloudy and
jbreatening, the streets ' approaching the
great suspension bridge" across East River,
both in New York and Brooklyn, were
Uironged with people, and the grand ceremonies
of the formal opening of the
to the public began according to the published
programme. The houses of Colonel Boebling, Chief Engineer
of the bridge, and of Mayor Low, of
Brooklyn, were decked with flowers and
bunting, and the coats-of-arms of New
York and Brooklyn.
From the towers of the great bridge the
National flag waved, and the span-across
the river was dotted with flags from one end
to the other. The committee representing the Brooklyn
Bridge Trustees escorted the President and
Cabinet to their carriages, other guests falling
into line and taking the carriages assigned
them. When the cairiages passed
the Seventh Regiment the command presented
arms. The military then broke into
column and maivhed down Fifth avenue
and Broadway to the City Hall Park, where
the members of the Common Council received
the President and Cabinet.
When the City 'Hall was reached the column
halted, and those in the carriages took
their places in the line on foot The inarch
over the bridge was a pretty sight as viewed
from the roof of a neighboring building.
The long line of soldiers in white and gold,
with their guns flashing in the sunlight and
the surging crowd of citizens, seemed to approach
the New York tower very slowly.
Contrasted with the size of the bridge, the
multitudes upon it appeared almost
From below the procession which
moved over the footway could scarcely be
seen at all. A temporary flooring had been laid over
that portion of the structure which will
serve as a roadway for' arriving and departing
trains. To this part of the building the
bulk of the spectators were consigned, the
chairs on the north being reserved for Brooklyn,
and those on the opposite for the gentlemen
crossing ihe bridge with the chief
dignitaries of the day.
It was half an hour after the time figuring
on the programme when the real business
of the hour began. Mr. J. S. T.
presided over the exercises, which
were opened with music by the Twenty-third
Regiment Band, and prayer by Bishop
Lutlejohn. Then followed President W. C.
Kingsley's presentation address, and the acceptance
addresses by the Mayors of Brooklyn
and New York. Levy played a cornet
solo, and Abram S. Hewitt came after him
with a long oration, of a historical character.
Bev. Dr. Storrs mad an eloquent
oration, and then the exercises came to a
close. The two cities had been duly and
formally wedded, and the icrial highway
declared open to travel. The great bridge is largely the product of
the severe winter of 1866-7. During that winter
the East River ferry-boats came to grief.
"Brooklyn business-men embarking on a Fulton
ferry-boat found themselves, after an hour's
cruising, in the vicinity of Hellgate. For days
the rlve"r was so choked with ice" as to be almost
impassable. Some boats, in beating against
ice-cakes in'a strong current, were driven down
around Governor's Island and then to Staten
Island. The inconvenience was great, but
the losses sustained by certain business
interests were such that a vigorous demand
was made for a bridge. Soon after men
of capital obtained a charter, and a bridge
company was formed with a capital of $5,000,-000.
The charter was afterward amended so
that the enterprise should be managed exclusively
by the authorities of the two cities,
Brooklyn agreeing to pay two-thirds of the
entire cost William CL Kingsley, of Brooklyn,
deserves to be called the lather of the great
bridge. As early as 1805 he employed an engineer
to draw plans and make estimates
for a suspension-bridge, and when the time
came for action he became the acknowledged
leader of the enterprise. May 23, 1867, John A.
Boebling was appointed Engineer. In September
of the same year he made his report of surveys,
plans and estimates. Work was
on the site of the foundation of the
Brooklyn tower January 3, 1870. Engineer
Boebling. however, did not live to see this
work begun. In the summer of 1809, while at
work on the location of the Brooklyn tower,
an incoming ferry-boat collided with some
timbers which crushed his foot, and he died of
lock-jaw about two weeks later. His son,
Washington A. Boebling, was called upon to
take up and complete his father's great work.
He was equal to the emergencj Although
falling a victim to the "caisson disease" in
December, 1871, he supervised the work from
his sick room. He has never recovered his
health and never will.
The construction of this gigantic cobweb for
travel has furnished an episode of engineering
the magnitude of which few appreciate.
The towers are 27G& feet in height. The
cables are anchored inland at a distance of 930
feet back from the towers on each side. The
anchorages are triumphs of stone-masonry,
119 by 133 feet at the base and rising to an elevation
of 90 feet above high-water mark.
Weighing about 60,000 tons each, they are of
course capable of resisting an enormous strain
from the cables. A stranger viewing the towers
for the first time naturally asks: "How was
it possible to obtain a proper foundation for
such structures so near the water?"
The query is easily answered. The submarine
section of the tower was constructed
above water in the open air and then
sunk to its bed deep down in the sand or
where the fishes were wont to disport This
was accomplished by the diving-bell and the
air The style of diving-bell used
is called a caisson. It resembles nothing so
much as an inverted chest. It must be lined
with boiler-iron, seamed air-tight, with means
of ingress and egress for msn and materials.
By the use of this caisson many formidable
difficulties have been surmounted and a perfect
foundation laid where the waves will
wash their mighty bases for ages. The foundation
is laid eighty feet below the surface of
the river and the granite masonry is true to a
hair's breadth. The cables sweep gracefully
over the top of the towers 276 feet in
height. The bridge floor, which the cables
sustain, is an immense steel framework consisting
of two systems of girders at right
angles to each other. The main girders, supporting
the floor proper, are graceful trusses
thirty-three inches deep, placed seven
feet six inches apart. To these are
attached four steel rope suspenders
from the cables. Parallel and longitudinal
trusses, Avith braces or stays, give the
combination strength in every direction. At
the towers the framework is firmly anchored.
The weight of the central span of the entire
suspended structure is 6,740 tons. It is estimated
that at no tim6 will this weight be increased
by cars, vehicles and passengers more
than 1,380 tons, giving a total maximum weight
of 8,120 tons. Of this enormous weight, 6,290
tons are sustained by the cables and 1,190 tons
by the suspensory stays of steel wire ropes diverging
from the tops of the towers to points
about fifteen feet apart along the bottom of
four of the vertical trusses. These stays extend
out from the towere 400 feet They form
important auxiliaries to the cables. The central
avenue of the bridge is to be used as a
footway. Its width is nineteen feet, and it is
elevated above the avenues on the sides some
ten feet. The side avenues are occupied by
cars moving from end to end by means of an
endless wire rope operated by a stationary engine.
The cables suspended from the great towers
are fifteen .and three-quarter inches thick. In
each cable there are 5,000 wires, the whole
mass being subdivided into skeins or strands
fashioned like skems of yarn or thread. Each
cable contains nineteen of these strands of 278
wires each, and each skein is a continuous
wire nearly 1,000,000 feet in length. The
first man to cross from tower to tower was E.
F. Farrington, the Master Mechanic of the enterprise,
who made the trip August 25, 1876.
Then the detail of the work went on, each day
adding to the number of wires from tower to
tower, until finally a light foot-bridge was run
across, and all who desired could walk from
one anchorage to the other over the tops of
the towers and across the river. Then the
cradles, ten in number, were got in position,
so that the men engaged in the cable-making
could regulate the wires, a matter of no small
difficulty, since the atmospheric eliects of the
sun and wind were such that frequently the
cables varied as much as half a foot in height
in the course of a das'. The deflections were,
however, all overcome, and the last wire Avas
run across October 15. 187S.
SOME STATISTICS.
Construction commenced January 3, 1S70.
Bridge completed 1883.
Length of river span. 1,595 feet 6 inches.
Length of both land spans, (930 feet each),
1,8G0 feet.
Length of Brooklyn approach, 971 feet
Length of New York approach, 1,562 feet 6
inches.
Total length of bridge, 5.9S9 feet
Width of bridge, 85 feet
Number of cables, 4.
Diameter of each cable, 15J inches.
First wiro run out May 29, 1877.
Length of wire in four cables, exclusive of
wrapping wire, 14,361 miles.
Length of each single wiro in cables, 3,579
feet.
Weight of four cables, exclusive of wrapping
wire, 3.58SJS tons.
Depth of tower foundation . below high
water, Brooktyn, 45 feet
Depth of tower foundation below high
water, New York, 78 feet
Total height of towers above high water,
278 feet .
' Clear height of bridge in center of river
span above high water, at 90 degrees Fahrenheit,
185 feet ,,,
Height of towers above high water, 119 feet
3 inches. - - .
Grade of roaftw&y, 3& feet in 100 feet.
Height of towers above roadway, 159 feet.
According to the estimate at first made the
bridge' with the land required would cost $10,-800,000.
Its actual cost when completed will'
be about $15,500,000.
THE BRIDGE TOLLS.
Cents.
One horse or horse and man . 5
One horse and vehicle 10
Two horses and vehicle 20
Foot passengers t
Two-horse trucks or wagons ij
Cattle, each 5
Sheep and hogs, each 3
The Brooklyn bridge is the longest suspen
Bion bridge in the world. The Victoria iron,
bridge over the St. Lawrence River, which is
9,437 feet long; Maintenon Aqueduct, stono,
16,367; Parkesburg, W. Va., iron bridge, 7,045 f
St. Charles, Mo., iron bridge, 6,536, and th
Firth of Tay bridge, 10.221, are the only struct?
ures that exceed it in length.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030272/1885-05-20/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Sergeant Phillips of Ibo Brooklyn Bridge
police station In Hands street Brooklyn was
informed by telephone from Police Captain Wll
llamas station Tn this city at 3 1 M that a
Blimp lookout must b kept for Prof Odiums
party Immediately Cant Ward rang up all
ranl
the reserves and sent them to promenade on
the south roadway and he and Sergeant Phil
rOBowII IIraeant Ihl
lips followed Word was Bent to the New York
end of the bridge to look carefully Into every
coach or covered wagon and I there was the
remotest suspicion that the jumper was on
hand the Police on the bridge were to be in
formed by telephone The telephone stations
tntons
are at tie bridge towers I was the Intention
of Capt Ward In making this arrangement to
have the police in the middle or near the mid
dle of the great span Informed In time to stop
the suspected vehicle. While this was going on the wagon was ap
proaching a point just half way between the
New York tower and the centre of the broad
upon Itt Is the potntwheruthe overfloor stays
begin These run from tbo bridge to the top of
the tower They form with the perpendicular
wires known as the suspenders a kind of lat
tice work of wires through which I man could
not crawl cosily and could not jump at all
Out from under a horse blanket In this wagon
suddenly sprang Odium tossed the blanket
aside and began to strip off his outer clothing
The wagon did not mop His soft black hat
went one way and his oid black frock coat an
other way He pulled his trousers inside out
in his eagerness to be off Than he klckedoff
a pair of wellworn Cn va shoes.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030272/1886-07-24/ed-1/seq-1</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Bootblacks nnd roslgnod tho leadership to
his brother Dan Ever since then ho has bon
planning to jump from the Brooklyn bridge.
On Tuesday of last week ho pays ho rodo up
from tho beach with a sporting man named
James A lironnnn liroillo began talking on
his hobby jumping off Brooklyn BrIdge and
said bo was willing to do It any time I there
was any money In It Hrnnnan said ho would
put up 100 that lirodlo couldnt do It Brodle
took him up and wont Into training for the
jump He mado another bet of S21 that ho
would jump from High Ilrldgo and early on
Sunday morning last hn Bays ho wont up with
a tow friends and jumped off Ho said at the
tlmo that ho bad jumped off High BrIdge onco
before and didnt think anything of It Ho felt
jubilant over winning the first bat nnd told all
hIs friends that in the latter part ot tile week
be would jump oft Brooklyn llridco and make
a name for himself
On Thursday ho went around the Fourth
ward and asked the advice of bin friends about
the best time to jump He said ho thought of
jumping that afternoon but they told him it
wouldnt bo a good tlmo and bo said ho would
postpone I Most of them thought the whole
thing was oil That evening he conoultod some
mute friend who are compositors in 1 news
paper ofuci and mado urrannnnonut with
thorn to witness the jump yesterday morning
Then be wint to the hack tenement at MS
Cllrvsl street whore ho lives with bin family
nnd ban two rooms on the north side two flights
up and went to tied
Yvstirdav morning his wlfo dressed him
Site was prnud of his courage and wanted to
do all she could to have him Huccood He had
got a long strip ot canton llnnnol and this was
wound around his loins abdomen and chost
Mvo plies thick I covered him from below hla
thighs up to his armnlis After it was tied lu
place he put on Wick knitted rod Jersey over
It 1 pair of heavy striped trousers and a pair
of old patent leather low shoes with thin sohH
Ills wife knollod a whit silk handkerchief
around blx iiuik over bin jiruuy Alter putting
ou his COlt and taking up his black soft felt lat
he started down town
Near the bridge bo met Dun Houston of 13
Elm street Ho said to Houston Im going
to jump the hridtre and I want you to come
along and help mi
Houston asked him If ho was In earnest
Droil lo answered that be was anti promlsea
Houston 115 and 1 Alit of clothes If he would
get u boat and pick him up Houston promised
to do It The two wont on down Frankfort
street and on the cornerof Gold street they
met Iuul Duller and Tim Drennan liroillo
mid tho salon offer to thorn and told thor
that bo was going to maul 101 from his jump
aL once unit moro In tho future and that ho
would divide up half the tlOO with anl friends
They all wont airing down Mouth street to the
Battery There Dan Houston hired a host for
two hours from an IByearold boy who had
charge of It Ho agreed to pay 30 coots nn hour
and loft his coat as security for tho no cents
The fur men got Into lie boat and rowed up
to Dover street ilook There they mot Jimmy
tho Boatman and took him on board They
paddled around for 1 while arid discussed the
juinn Brodle f aid
Ive decided Im going to
Well boys lolnl jump
the Brooklyn bridge
The boat pulled up Into Dover street dock
again Brodle got out shook bands with them
and halfpast 11 oclock be started
all nt 1 oclok up
Frankfurt street to tie bridge At a quarter
past 12 bi carne back and said that the wind
was too strong lunttbpn Tbe boat was tied up
at the pier until IX oclock when Brodle said
that he won going to jump for certain and
started again up Fran fort street The boat
pulled out with Dan Houston Tim Brennan
Paul Butler and Jimmy ibo Boatman on
board and hovered in the river south ot tho
bridge The tide wan just beginning to run
out Tugs and ferryboats wore continually
passing but none nf them took any notice of
tbe boat or Its 1 occupants
Brodle bad bad two drinks of whIskey dur
ing the morning before be loft his four friends
In the boat Ho went up Frankfort street
alone At Nassau street bo met Jerry Kane
and ISS
Jerry Im going to lump the bridge Ive
got 2U cents and I wont need only two to get
out on the drive Conies In and have a drink
The two went Into Kosmnks Kane drank
beer and Brodln whiskey They went out and
stood by the wagon road over the bridge Bugs
Waterman was standing thero
Bugs said Brodle Im going jump the
bridge Come along and see me
Waterman said he would Brodle must have
found semi more money about him than the
20 cents for he took a dollar bill from his
pocket and said
Dora this U my last dollar Come and havo
ft drink
Ho and Waterman wont Into Kosmaks
When they came out Kano asked Brodie If ho
was In earnest about jumping oft the bridge
Brodle said ho was nnd that hn was going to
start at onco Kane left htm and started down
Frankfort street to Dover street dock
Waterman remained with Brodle Brodlo
stopped threo or four wagons and asked them
ItolPd wallns Llom
to take him over the bridge. the bridge
He grasped the strlngnleoa underneath time
Jo
flooring with both hands and bung there for
ton seconds facing up the river Tbo police
men saw It was no use to attempt to stop him
and ran for tbo New tork end of the bridge
Brodyswung to and fro twice trying to steady
himself before bo let go tils legs were does
togetber. Each of his 1 friends toll him that ho did
I old I B going to jump tim bridge and
Ivn dono it Havent 11 Lvery one of you
saw me do I Uldnt you
Houston torn open Drndlo shirt produced r
bottln of brandy and rnbbd bin chest with the
spirits Broil took no drink ultl I ho got 10
land Tin boat ww roivoil over to the pier at
tile foot uf tho bridge tower and Brodlo and
Houston woro landed on tho nplles thorn
Houston I I had limt his hat and I boo All I this
time Duller was struggling about in the wntnr
where ho had boon left An onr hud binn
thrown to him or ho might havo drowned Ho
shouted for hull and two policemen and a
crowd came A lug and time bout went for him
and took him annum Brodlo didnt lIke his
placo on the stubs dived oft mind nwiun across
lho slip to Dover street tier A rope wus
thrown to him and he Imbed up on tbo plor
BrldgD Policeman Laly had boon on a dead
run down from the bridge entrance and wns
seen coming down the pier Brodle got bnck
into tho but
Fetch that boat Into the dock Bald the po
liceman Come In here
JJo you want lo arrest me 1 Bald Brodlo
No Wont you touch mo 2.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1886-07-24/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<!I know there is more but I cannot understand the text :/ >
	<text>'? steve" Brodie uud a friend named Waterman wire
ttaudlag at t!,o entrance to tho Carriage-way of
thu Brooklyn Bftdga at a iiuartei- before 2
yesterday afternoon. Carrtagaa aud wagons passed
unuii their w.iy to Brooklyn, and at bat Brodie.
lie had made the Jump on a wager of MOO With a " sport?
ing ' mun named James llr-nnan, whom he had met on
the Brighton Beach track, lt ls generally believed, how?
ever, that Brodie made the leap out of pure deviltry. It
ls a t ti I ii _* that he has been thlnkiug about for two years.
A week ac Sunday, lt ls said, he Jumped sueeessfully
from niifh Bridge and since that time he ha. been Intent
upon tri lng the non niore dangerous leap from tlie
Brooklyn Bridge. Tba time for Hie )ump was set forty
eight hours beforehand, but only a few were in tne
secret. Brodie wsa protected bv braces
and bandages. Otherwise, lt ls believed he could
not have made tha Jump in safety.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1901-07-26/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Chief Engineer C. C. Martin, of the Brooklyn
Bridge, returned late yesterday afternoon from
his country home at Tewksbury. Mass.. and
spent a good part of last night superintending
the repairs to the bridge.
Mr. Martin was quoted as saying that the re
pairs would be completed, and the structure re
stored to Its normal strength by m*>n to-day.
At 1 o'clock this morning the night force of
twelve men was still on the bridge, and those
in charge said the men would continue at work
until men came this morning to take their
places. Inquiries regarding the safety of the Brooklyn^
Bridge and the suspected negligence of the
bridge officials were started yesterday by the
District Attorney's office, the Police Department
and the Health Board. If it ascertained that de
fects In the bridge structure were known by the
bridge officials in time to prevent the breaks) en
Wednesday, the grand jury will be asked to
make an investigation.
Gustavus C. Henning. a consulting engineer.
who supervised the construction of the section
of the bridge on which the breaks occurred, de
clared yesterday that the bridge should be built
anew. He said that officials were warned at
the time the bridge was built that the materials
were faulty, but their use was Insisted on to
save cost.
Controller Coler argued that if tunnels had
been constructed between Brooklyn and Man
hattan for the trolley lines there would have
been no reason for overloading the bridge. The
structure, it Is declared, never was intended for
trolley traffic.
It was ascertained yesterday that the iron
work of the bridge had not been repainted in
three years, and much of it was rusty. Runt
appeared to be a cause for the breaks in the
bridge structure.
No regular systems of Inspections has been
in use on the bridge under the present adminis- ¦
tration. The engineers can learn of injuries to
the structure only by accidental reports.
Traffic on the north side of the bridge was sus
pended yesterday, but a few trains and trolley
cars were run. shuttle fashion, on the south
side all day and all night. Many thousands of
persons walked over the bridge.
The ferries between Manhattan anJ Brooklyn
¦were crowded at the rush hours. The division of
travel from the bridge to the ferries did not
much affect the railroads in Brooklyn
Workmen removed broken parts' of th«» bridge
yesterday, and it was said that new parts would
be substituted within forty-eight hours. The en
gineers of the bridge declare that when traffic
is resumed the bridge will be as strong as it
ever was. There are four main cables, and each is Balls
i to the same breakage. What would cause a
1 breakage? Well, what would break a straw?
' Can you Imagine anything breaking without
| having too much weight placed on it? I can
[ not, v V-'
"The trouble lies in the fact that the suspend
ers are of the poorest material. I ought to
know because I not only designed it and super
! intended the construction of it. but also super
: intended the construction of the material. WWhetn t
I advised the use of better material the author
ities said that the cities could not afford It. :
"There are two things about the bridge that
: are all right. These are the towers. They will
I stand for an indefinite length of time, and I do
not believe enough weight can be put on them
to affect them in the least. As for the remain
der of the bridge— well, unless it is reconstruct
ed with a much greater foundation of strength,
or unless the traffic it is now called on to sus
tain be decreased enormously, some day there 1
will be a terrible catastrophe."
DEFECTIVE WIRE WAS USED
MATTER OF NOTORIETY WHEN THIN
BRIDGE WAS BUILDING THAT MA
TERIAL below STANDARD .f
WAS ACCEPTED. r ~
There are many who remember that wtrv
which was tested and found defective was used
In the construction of the bridge. It was a mat
ter of notoriety at the time that some of th»
wire that had been submitted for use was found
of a grade lower than the standard and was re
jected by the examining engineers, but was of
fered ag&in and accepted. It was admitted be
fore the bridge was finished that some of this
wire was used. Where it Is no man can tell now,
and It may be that the break that is causing so
much' trouble and subjecting the people of both ;
sides of the river to such inconvenience may be j
some of this wire that was smuggled in by the
use of influence or money.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1920-10-31/ed-1/seq-84/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>A FEW days ago a youthful
Westerner ? well, he isn't
exactly youthful, but in
pome mysterious fashion he
manages not to grow up?burst into
the office and gasped :
"They're taking Brooklyn Bridge
apart!" He sat in a chair to col?
lect himself. "Brooklyn Bridge!" he
emphasized. " After forty - five
years!"
In spite of the fact that he was
addressing a group of Manhattanese
who had grown somewhat callous to
Brooklyn Bridge, condescendingly
looking upon it as something too
closely identified with the borough
of alarm clocks and rubber plants,
he caused something of a sensation. One who is a native of the big
city and does not know in what ven?
eration Brooklyn Bridge is held by
all outsiders?aii^l, truth to tell, by
most natives?might find difficulty
in appreciating the Westerner's agi?
tation. But in any case, at least
two of his statements require clear?
ing up.
In the first place, it is not forty
five years since the bridge was fin?
ished, but only thirty-seven. The
span ?vas turned over to the public
on May 24, 1883, and so the four
decades will not be up until May
24, 1023. A tablet states, however,
that it was dedicated in October,
1875.
Paint to Cost $85.000
Nor, as intimated, is it true that
the bridge is being taken apart. It
is a fact that extensive alterations
and repairs are being made, among
the first, improvements decided upon
being a reinforced floor along the
entire length of the span and a new
coat of paint. The painting alone
will cost $85,000.
Hew and there, too, sections of
the steel work are being strength?
ened, and the old bolts?they are
actually pins?arc being replaced by
new one?.
The Westerner was greatly
wrought up when he discovered the
metal pieces being plucked from the
venerable structure- sort of sever?
ing the threads, you know, from
among the old?hut let no one jump
lo the conclusion that his is an
isolated case.
A walk across the span any day
when the workers are at their tasks
will show this is not the fact,
Many stop to watch the riveters
at work. In New York City rubber?
necking is one of the recognized and
established diversions, but there is
something different about these
?.razor**. They see in these overalled
figures not mere mechanics engaged
in unscrewing nuts, repainting iron
work and replacing boards, but
votaries of a holy task performing
sacred rites on an edifice, grown
hallowed through the generations.
"I Was There"
The other day a graybeard paused
in his walk and beckoned to one of
the workers. The worker was in a
group of others on a cord at the far
side of the elevated rails, and it
meant considerable trouble for him
to cross over the narrow footpath
to the middle roadway for pedes,
trians, but he did it. Thus do th
mellowing influences of sentimenl
and tradition exert themselves!
"See you are making repair-,'
orTered the graybeard.
"Representing some iron com
pany?" inquired the workingman
eying the other suspiciously.
"a\"o. Live in Brooklyn. I wa
there when they opened this bridge '
"Yeh?"
"Yes. Abo Hewitt made the
speech. Fine speech. The Presi
dent of the United States w 13 then
and so was the Governor ind th
Mayor of \* w York Brooklyi
didn't belong to New Vori; then,
you know and a lot o^ people."
"Must have been a great sight."
"Yes. You born in Brooklyn'."'
"No." The workingman showed
a trace of uneasiness. "Kansas. But
1
it's a great old bridge," he hastened
to assert.
"Yes?"
"Yes. Phsaw, none of them other
bridges can compare with it even
yet."
"Can it be possible?"
The Same Steel Pieces
"Sure See them big steel cross
pieces underneath? Them things
that support the rails, you know?
Well, them has been there ever
since the bridge was put up and
they're as good as ever. No, I'm not
kiddin'. You take them same pieces
on the Manhattan Bridge, now, and
they're three or four times as heavy
and not a bit better."
"Really?"
"Sure. Say. I been workin' on
bridges all my life and 'f I don't
know a bridge no one does. It's a
great old bridge, I'll tell the world."
"I'm glad to hear you say ro,"
said the gruybeard. He shook hands
solemnly with the mechanic. "Too
bad you weren't born in Brooklyn,"
he called back as he moved away.
"Another of thorn Brooklyn Bridge
nuts," remarked the ironworker as
he started back for his aerie. "But
she's a good old bridge at that."
She is. Grover Whalen, win
ought to know, seeing he is the Coni
missiner of Plant, and Structures
and therefore responsible for i lie
condition of the structure, insist?
most enthusiastically that she is
swearing that just as soon as thai
new floor is down, and a few of the
bolts?pins?are tightened up or re?
placed, she'll be as good as new.
?No Danger of Falling
From time to time disturbing
rumors have been heard that th
ancient link was about to fall down
or was sagging dangerously in spots
but each time the experts wen
called upon to make an examinatioi
they found, as much to their owi
astonishment as that of any one else
that the figure of speech was liter
ally true.
Brooklyn Bridge not only is per
forming all the service original 1;
set out for it, but is easily and safel;
carrying a trafile several time
greater than dreamed of by its wi',1
est protagonist. In UM s the R. R. T. furnished
figures to the Public Service Com?
mission showing that trolley cars
had crosse,] ii1(, bridge 1,000,000
Brooklyn Bridge from the Docks
times that year and thai in nddifion
there had been 800,000 trips be?
tween Manhattan and Brooklyn by
elevated trains.
As it is the practice to take the
count of ira Hie on all the city
bridges between October 15 and
November 15, when travel 's con
idered normal, the ligures for L920
10 the present rime are not \ ?"., com?
piled, but there are others which
will lie found helpful.
Whereas, in 1912 only 3 913
vehicles used 'ie two roadw, ys of
rriIEY span;? on (lie bridge at midnight?and also all the
?* hours from noon till then
the bridge daily, 6,605 passed over
them ?? a a: two . fo ir hours, in
1919.
In 191 ' y cars carried 1 19,
P93 persi m a d iy, and in 1919, 130,
356. Ele1 lie ;' 11 ofl' a little
la it year as compared with 1912,
but even so an average of 106,200
i ossi d by ti roui e bei v, e? n morn?
ing and eve
The V;.io:iV Population
? - ; - ? ti -a ? i hat by ; i ey
? a ?,-.-- a a lone 36,357,
d the bridge in VI'.'.
add d to thes : the
un er of those who walk across or
han 6,600 motor
ear i and v tous daily it
is coi I ha i throng equal t(
the entire population of the United
States crosses Brooklyn Bridge every
year. For twenty year , until 1903 to
Le exact, when the Williarasfaf
Bridge was opened, Brooklyn Bridge
remained the onb span across the
East River.
It would take a lot of print to
give the history of ; .ins old
link. A crea:: n .it took
hold of the romantic like a fever.
No theatrical pr ?iealing
with the danger-? at city
was complete which did not show
somewhere in the scenic distance a
reproduction of the span. In the
shadow of the stone approaches or
underneath the wharfing would be
shown a pirates' retreat, where the
beautiful heroine inevitably becam?
a prisoner. Many persons sougl.i
to incorporate the glory of ?K
bridge and their own by perform
ing strange or dangerous dcedi
t-pon it.
Steve Brodie'? Leap
?Steve Brodie gained fame and fol
tune by being the first ?to leap fror
the bridge into the river and survivi
and' he soon had several imitator:
some of them successful and son'
not.</text>
	  </result>
	  <!This marks the start of 10 Extra articles for topic 2!>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88085947/1906-11-30/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>F BROOKLYN BRIDGE SHOULD FALL
IF BROOKLYN BRIDGE SHOULD FALL THE CABLES WOULD SNAP AND THE TOWERS WOULD COLLAPSE TOWARD RIVER
NEW YORK, Nov. 30— There Is
a possibility that, between the
hours of 7 and 9 a. m. or 5 and 7
p. m. some day, the public will be
startled with the news of one of
the most terrible calamities in his
tory.
This alarming statement is
based upon the words of Vice
President John F. Calderwood, of
the Brooklyn Rapid Transit Co.,
which leases the railroad facilities
on towering Brooklyn bridge.
This is what Calderwood said:
"While the operating depart
ment is in no way responsible for
the present conditions on Brook
lyn bridge, you can rest assured
that we are keeping the records
in such shape that in the event of
a calamity not only the men who
are In direct connection with this
operation will share its responsi
bility, but all others who are in
any way responsible for the pres
ent conditons."
The statement was made In ref
erence to the Brooklyn Rapid
Transit Co.'s vain effort to control
the constantly growing traffic on
TEMPERANCE MEETING.
Mrs. Marguerite Munns, state
president of Western Washington
W. C. T. U., will address a tem
perance meeting in the Third Pres
byterian church, First ay. and
Magnolia st., Sunday evening, the
services beginning at 7:30. The
meeting is held under tbe auspices
of the Spokane W. C. T. U. and a
large attendance is desired.
CASTOR IA
For Infants and Children.
Hie Kind You Have Always Bcagli
3ears the
■Signature
of
Remington
Typewriter
Sales
lastyearweregreat,
but our business for
the first three-quar
ters of 1906 ex
ceeds that of the
entire year 1905
Typewriter* come and typewriter* go
But the Remington runt on (orevet
REMINGTON TYPEWRITER CO.,
110 Washington St., Spokane
SPOKANE PltfnSS, NOVEMBER 29,1906
the enormous steel span which
joins Manhattan and Brooklyn.
Night and morning when the
vast throng of workers are pass
ing to and from their places of em
ployment 450 elevated cars, each
weighing, empty, 65,000 . pounds,
and 300 surface cars, each with a
weight of, 43,000 pounds, pass over
the swaying suspension in the
course of every 60 minutes. It is
roughly estimated that the weight
of these cars, with their passen
gers, is more than 40,000,000
pounds.
From time to time for years
there have been alarming reports
that Brooklyn bridge was gradual
ly, though surely, giving way un
der this terrific strain. Never be
fore, however, has such an admis
sion come from an authoritative
source as Calderwood. Railroad
experts and those employed by the
city have long been put to their
wits' end to contrive some meas
ure of relief.
Within two years a second
bridge has been built and opened
across the East river, joining Man-
UNION TAILORS
5 WASHINGTON STREET
We have just received 25 full bolts of all wool woolens from our New York
agents. Goods that sold for $3 to $5 per yard. We will make suits or overcoats to
order for $15.00. Other high price merchant tailors charge you $30 to $40
OUR PRICE SATURDAY
ONE DAY ONLY
Remember, ono day only.
What we hive left we have orders to ship balance of these woolens to our
Seattle store.
Our guarantee should linings or any part of garment not wear satisfactorily wo
will renew sam free of charge inside of oue year.
Don't Miss This Sale as You Will
Never Get It Again This Season
OPEN SATURDAY EVENING UNTIL 10:30 P, M. EVERY YARD GUARAN
TEED IMPORTED GOODS WORTH $3 TO $5 PER YARD.
UNION TAILORS
5 WASHINGTON STREET
hattan with the Williamsburg sec
tion of Brooklyn, at a cost of $17,-
--000,000. A third bridge Is now in
course of construction and a
fourth projected. A tunnel under
the river is also in course of con
struction, but traffic continues to
increase rapidly.
In the course of each 24 hours
no less than half a million people
cross Brooklyn bridge. It is not
uncommon for 50,000 people to be
upon the bridge at one time during
rush hours.
Engineers declare that the
heaviest strain upon tho bridge is
upon tho four great suspension
cables, each 15 3-4 inches in diam
eter. The length of each single
wire in these cables is 3,578 feet
and 6 inches. The ultimate
strength of each»cable Is estimated
at 12,000 tons. Each cable con
tains 5,290 parallel galvanized
steel oil coated wires, closely
wrapped to a solid cylinder. Tbe
permanent weight suspended from
the cables is 14,680 tons.
If Brooklyn bridge should give
way, according to the speculation
of engineers, it would likely be due
to a snapping of one or more of the
cables, with the possibility of the
towers caving in toward the river.
The tower on the Manhattan end
of the bridge contains 40,945 cubic
yards of masonry. The Brooklyn
tower contains 38,000 cubic yards.
The height of these towers is 278
feet. The distance from the road
way to the river is about 135
feet.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85035722/1901-05-18/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>lli Brooklyn Bridive
Shows I m me use Superiority Over
Old Structure—Cost unil Statistics
of a Great Engineering Feat.
Across the strait, miscalled the East
river, that separates the boroughs of
Manhattan and Brooklyn, in the city
of New York, scientists, engineers and
laborers are erecting a magnificent
bridge. This structure, which is rap
idly nearing completion, is , ue of t'.ie
wonders of the opening century and
will probably remain one for many
years to come. It far surpasses the
well known and far famed Brooklyn
bridge that is always seen in views of
the eastern metropolis. The old bridge
is now the greatest suspension bridge
in l he world, but the new one will as
far surpass it in size and strength as
the Brooklyn bridge did preceding
structures of the kind.
As the old bridge is the only one that
furnishes an adequate basis of com
parison, contrasting the figures of the
old and new bridges best illustrates
the greatness of the more recent
structure. The new bridge will be
four times as strong as the Brooklyn
bridge. Each of its four cables will
be about twice as stout as those that
support the span of the Brooklyn
bridge, and in other respects it will be
stronger.
The dimensions of the new East river
bridge as officially given and those of
the old one are as follows: Length of
entire bridge between terminals, 7,200
feet. The old bridge is 0,000 feet. The
length of channel span of the new bridge
is 1,000 feet. The Brooklyn bridge has
only 4M> feet less of actual channel
span, bnt in total length of span the
new bridge will claim the record by
1,200 feet. The extreme width of the
new bridge is 118 feet, that of the o'.ti.
one 8.7 feet. The steel towers of the
new bridge are about 59 feet higher
than the masonry spires of the old. The
cap of the steel work is 335 feet above
high water, while the corresponding di
mension of the Brooklyn bridge is 270
feet.
The new bridge will furnish accom
modations for four surface railroad
tracks, two tracks for elevated trains,
il M I
Hof I
PIER TOWERS OF THE NEW EAST RIVER
BRIDGE.
two roadways for vehicles, two foot
ways for pedestrians and two cycle
paths. The old bridge has only live
parallel pathways—two for carriages,
wagons and trolley cars, two for the
third rail electric or elevated cars and
one for pedestrians.
In spite of its superiority in size and
strength the enormous advance in bridge
building and steel work has made it
possible to construct the new bridge at
not much over half the cost of the old
one. The Brooklyn bridge cost about
in round numbers $13,000,000. The cost
of the new one when completed will be
about $S,000,000. The new bridge
stretches across the river somewhat
over a mile north of the Brooklyn
bridge. Owing to a bend in the East
river the new bridge is considerably
east of the old one. The contrast in size
of the two is best shown when they are
viewed from the river. It is then clear
ly seen how the piers of the new bridge
tower above those of the Brooklyn.
The new bridge extends from the foot
of Delancey street, Manhattan, to South
Fifth and South Sixth streets, Brook</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045774/1922-07-30/ed-1/seq-8/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>$50,000,000 BRIDGE
Contlnned from First Page.
agreement with Col. Boebllng about the
present safety of the Brooklyn Bridge.
He said:
y "We havo in this department some
of the best engineers in the world and
they have assured me that under present
traffic conditions the Brooklyn
Bridge Is as safe as It ever has been."
Mr. Whalen went on to explain how
the slipping of the cables was dfscov
eretl in mo cgurso m mo uraumrjt uau;
Inspection and resulted In his order
ruling motor traffic off the structure,
asserting the engineers had informed
him the slip was due to overloading and
that the load must be reduced at once.
He pointed out, however, that t#ie bridge
had not shown the slightest sign. The Brooklyn Bridge must Me put \ r.
in condition to carry all the traffic, both ; 1
motor and horse drawn vehicles, that | t
there is room for. The clfy cannot | t
spare the bridge. The Williamsburg i *
Bridge can take no more traffic than it ! '
is now carrying and the Manhattan
Bridge, too, is almost taxed to the limit, h
It is impossible to strengthen the cables li
of the Brooklyn Bridge or even to put, I
them back in place without reconstruct- \
lng the span, and before than can be C
dope a new bridge must be built. Thls'j t
is the question I want to put before the c
Board of Estimate at the earliest pos- ! r
sible moment. | t
"I have no plan, not even a tentative c
one. All I know Is that the Brooklyn j
Bridge must "bo rpbulli and that It can- j 3
not be rebuilt until there Is a, new t
bridge. This new bridge will be needed p
anyhow, for with the rapid growth or t
population, traffic between Manhattan f
Rnd Brooklyn Is constantly on the In- f
crease." t
Mr. Wlialen went on to say that he c
would not recommend the building of s
the new bridge across the river south I
of the Brooklyn Bridge or between the
T. obable cost- of the proposed bridge, It
i Interesting to note that the vehicular
innel between New York and New Jerey,
an elaborate twin tube structure,
dth two roadways In each direction
nd sidewalks, as well, to coet, for
[instruction, according to the estimates,
38,000,000. The coet of the real estate
i estimated at 12,BOO.000 and the equip*
tent will cost about $750,000.
The announcement about the slipping
f the cables, said now to be due to the
illure of the rollers under the saddles
t the top of the towers to function
roperly, did not have the sllghest effect
n the Brooklyn crowds, though d. few
ersons looked curiously at the tops of
le fine Xone towers. The only thine
ally noticeable about the old Brooklyn
irtdge was that In places it needed
alntlng badly.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045774/1921-11-27/ed-1/seq-69/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Before the Brooklyn E
lyn had a population of
Brooklyn's population i
population, 2,284,103. A
seekers have moved over
Remember! Sometii
portunities under our no!
them. Right here, near
same opportunity for gi
the Brooklyn Bridge was
Camden lies in the
Philadelphia that Brookl
What Brooklyn is to N
be to Philadelphia. Phils
over the Delaware River. Today, with bridges,
s 2,018,356, and Manhattan's
lmost a million and a half home
the bridges into Brooklyn.
nes we are too close to the op- ^
se to see and take advantage of ^
Philadelphia?Camden has the
rowth that Brooklyn had after
i built.
t
same geographical position to
lyn did to "old" New York City,
ew York City, Camden should
idelphia home-seekers will flow
er Bridge just as New York.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84026749/1922-07-31/ed-1/seq-5/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Brooklyn Bridge Good for 200
Years More Service, Engi
neer Declares.
? ? I
By (OkniopoiKao Nm
TKENTON, N. J.. July 11.?Col. 1
Washington A. Itoebllng. eigbiy five,
laughed at reports that historic
Brooklyn Bridge may l>e, (ailing
down.
"Nonsense," said the famous engi
neer and builder of the suspension
structure, which, when completed
some forty years ago was hailed ha
one pf the seven wonders of the mod
ern world.
"That bridge is good for 150 or
200 years' more service," he said.
"There Is not the slghtest danger.
All this excitement about*\wo of the
main supporting cables slipping 'o
one side is foolish; if they didn't
slip, one end of ihe bridge would fall
down. My engineers' reports show
the cables have not slipped longitu
dinally. The excitement being raised
is for the purpose of hastening con
struction of a new supplemental
bridge." '
As to rebuilding the bridge, which
he completed as a young engineer
when his father, who designed tn?
structure, died. Mr. Koebling said:
"Brooklyn Bridge Is carrying six
to cfcfht times the amount of traffic
of Its early days. There is no neces
sity to rebuild It. for it will last from
150 to 200 years."
An average of 300,000 persons t ross
Brooklyn Bridge daily, in street cars,
elevated trains and other vehicles,
To relieve the strain upon it, the
bridge was closed to heavy motor
traffic six weeks ago by New V'ork
I city authorities.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86090439/1901-06-06/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>IGGEST OF BRIDGES
SEVEN THOUSAND FEET OF SPAN
TO HANG OVER EAST RIVER.
Comparlaoa MHO llrookly* Hrldg*
Iho.o Immense Superiority O»»r
Old Structure—Cost nnd Stntlutlc*
of a Great Enalneerluc Feat.
Across the strait, ml sen lip.l the Enst
river, that separates the nortfSghs of
Manhattan and Brooklyn, in the city
of New York, scientists, engineers and
laborers an* erecting a magnificent
bridge. This structure, which Is rap
idly nearing completion, is one of the
wonders of the opening century and
will probably remain one for many
years to come. It far surpasses the
well known and far famed Brooklyn
bridge that is always seen In views of
the eastern metropolis. '■‘The old bridge
Is now the greatest suspension bridge
in the world, but the new one will as
far surpass it in sise and strength as
the Brooklyn bridge did preceding
structures of the kind.
As the old bridge is the only one that
furnishes an adequate basis of com
parison, contrasting the figurea of the
old and new bridges best illustrates
the greatness of the more recent
structure. The new bridge will be
four times as strong as the Brooklyn
bridge. Each of Its four cables will
be about twice as stout as those that
support the span of the Brooklyn
bridge, and in other respects it w|U be
stronger.
The dimensions of the new East rivet
bridge as officially given and those ot
the old one are as follows: length ot
entire bridge between terminals, 7,2(10
feet. The old bridge Is 6.000 feet. The
length of channel span of the new bridge
Is 1,000 feet. The Brooklyn bridge has
only 4*i feet less of actual channel
span, but in total length of span the
new bridge will claim the record by
1,200 feet. The extreme width of the
new bridge is 118 feet, that of the old
one 85 feet. The steel towers of the
new bridge are about 59 feet blgbet
than the masonry spires of the old. The
cap of the steel work is 335 feet above
high water, while the corresponding di
mension of the Brooklyn bridge is 27t
feet.
The new bridge will furnish accom
modations for four surface railroad
tracks, two tracks for elevated trains
PTEH TOWERS OF THE NEW RAW HIVES
Bit IDO E.
two roadways for vehicles, two foot
ways for pedestrians and two cycle
paths. The old bridge has only five
parallel pathways—two for carriages,
wagons and trolley cars, two for the
third rail electric or elevated cars and
one for pedestrians.
In spite of its superiority In size and
strengththeenormous advance in bridge
building and steel work has made it
possible to construct the new bridge at
not much over half the cost of the old
one. The Brooklyn bridge cost about
in round numbers $15,000,000. The cost
of the new one when completed will be
about $8,000,000. The new bridge
stretches across the river somewhat
over a mile north of the Brooklyn
bridge. Owing to a bend in the East
river the new bridge is considerably
east of the old one. The contrast In size
of the two Is best shown when they are
viewed from the river. It is then clear
ly seen how the piers of the new bridge
tower above those of the Brooklyn.
The new bridge extends from the foot
of Delancey street, Manhattan, to South
Fifth and South Sixth streets, Brook
lyn.
Figures showing the Immense
strength and size of the new bridge
might be given almost Indefinitely. It
will contain, for example, about 1,500,-
000 feet of timber, 10,000 cubic yards
of concrete, 45,000 cubic yards of stone
masonry and 1,600 tons of cable an
chor steel in each anchorage. In the
steel towers and the shore spans were
used 12,000 tons of steel. In making
the steel cables there will be used 5.000
tons of steel wire and steel castings.
The new bridge will in every way be a
remarkable structure and a monument
to the skill of American engineers and
steel workers.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86063592/1903-12-19/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>i ine general puoiic was nut psr
tultted to cross tbe bridge today and
,tuua was avoided the possibility of
crush such as wss wllnesiiiwl at lha
opening of the Brooklyn bridge and
which resulted In the deaths of more
than a score of persons. Hut one
roadway of the new bridge' is entirely
completed and this will probably be
opened to traffic tomorrow or Monday
It is expected that the other roadway
and the paths fur pedes) rains will he
ready within a few weeks.
In general appearance the bridge
SiH-ms tuucb more mafmive than the
old Brooklyn bridge, but at the same
time It Is much less graceful. In
length, width, height and the number
of Its promeusdes and trolley tracks
the new structure surpssses the
old. The Manhattan terminal of tbe
Hew structure Is at IManeey street
while the Williamsburg etui Is at the
South Fifth street. Jn the construe
tlon of these great terminals and ap
proaches whole blocks of buildings
were rated. across the fol
lowing November. The cables were
finished in August of 1902.
The opening of tbe new bridge Is ex
pected to relieve somewhat tbe over
burden of traffic on the Brooklyn
bridge. This measure of roller, how
ever, will not be nearly so great, as
might be supposed at the first glance
at the situation, for the reason that
the great bulk of traffic that will use
the now structure have heretofore
crossed the river by ferry and have
not used the Brooklyn bridge to any
extent. The ultimate relief of tbe
Brooklyn bridge crush lies In the com
plutlon of the third brldgo across the
Rust rlver already under construction
at a point about midway between the
Brooklyn brldgo and the Williamsburg
struct uro opened today. In addition
to those three bridges a fourth is to
connect Manhattan with the Brooklyn
shore by way of Ulackwell's Island, so
that New York In a few years will be
able to lsy claim to the title of the city
of magnificent bridges.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82016014/1905-01-28/ed-1/seq-10/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>I HE engineers of the
department of bridges
of the city of New
York have decided
that the time Is not
far distant when the
Brooklyn bridge must
be condemned and re
built. It is also stated authoritatively
" that, while there is no Immediate dan
gler to be apprehended from the struc
ture's condition, the completion of the
new Manhattan bridge and the subway
tunnel, both now under construction,
hould be the limit of the old bridge's
term of usefulness and that its recon
Btruction on a vastly more comprehen
sive scale should be entered upon at
that time.
At the time of Its completion twenty-one
years ago last May many posi
tive statements were made concerning
the great achievement. One of them
was to the effect that the giant struc
ture would prove adequate to the de
mands of traffic for generations to
come. It did not take long to demon
' Btrate the fallacy of that proposition.
Its first decade was scarcely spent be
fore the utter inadequacy of the won
der was apparent to all. It was also
declared on the occasion of the bridge's
opening to traffic that it was prac
tically indestructible,- an enduring
monument to the skill of its builders
and the progressive spirit of the citi
tens of the metropolis. The last rem
nant of that belief if, indeed, it ever
prevailed at all was shattered a few
years ago when it was discovered that
seventeen of the steel girders which
held the beautiful structure in suspen
sion had succumbed beneath the un
foreseen strain which they had been
called upon to endure. The Brooklyn Bridge rail
way was opened to the public on Sept.
24. 18S3, and since that date the serv
ice has expanded from a single , car
every five minutes to a four car train
every fifty-five seconds during the busy
time of the day. The passenger traffic
by the rls of various powerful corpo
rations which were able to accumulate
enormous treasure by their ability to
influence the carrying trade and by dis
crimination in rates to drive individual
dealers and small companies out of
business.
The evil became so unendurable that
some of the states began to seek a
remedy In legislation. Some of them
created railroad commissions, clothed
with drastic powers to fix maximum
rates and to superintend all the minu
tiae of railroad management. The state
of Massachusetts was content to under
take advisory powers. " The states in
the great grain growing belt were un
able to enforce their radical measures
of railroad reform, and, the offenders
declined to accept the advice of the
Bay State, excellent though it undoubt
edly was.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84020645/1904-04-10/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Many observant pedestrians who take
their daily constitutional across the new
and recently opened Brooklyn bridge
have noticed, an unusual amount of vi
bration In certain parts of the new struc
ture. In short, there
has grown up a considerable amount of
talk in the Eastern district regarding this
“shakiness," as it Is called, of the big
bridge, and several of the observers of
Inquiring mind have written letters to
the Eagle asking whether or not this Is
as It should be or If It Is not a symptom
of weakness and danger. The fact of the matter is that the
bridge vibrates noticeably In two sec
tions only, the land spans, which extend
fiom the towers on either side to the
great stone anchorages. This Is true, not
in theory only, hut by actual observations
made by an Engle reported with Instru
ments designed to measure the vibra
tions.
Of course, the only basis upon which
to frame conclusions in regard to the
structure Is a comparison with Brooklyn
bridge. As the Brooklyn bridge Is be
ing constantly crossed and recrossed by
endless lines of bridge and trolley cars,
heavily freighted with passengers, It Is
unfair to the older structure to make ob
servations on the Williamsburg bridge,
which has no car lines, and draw edn
cluslons detrimental to the older bridge.
There can be little question, however,
that so far as the towers are concerned,
th'. massive pillars of granite which sus
tain Brooklyn brldgo are much more
rigid and unyielding than are the steel
towers of the newer bridge.
In testing the vibration of the Wil
liamsburg bridge on the occasion of
the passage of heavy trucks, which fur
nish the greatest strain which the struc
ture has yet been called upon to bear, the
Eagle reporter obtained these results;
The vibrations are greatest about 200 feet
Inside the towers on the land spans which
connect the great river span, or bridge
proper, with the supported roadways
which have been built for approaches.
The bridge In Its entirety, from the
plsra In Williamsburg to the terminal In
Manhattan, really consists of five sepa
rate and Independent structures, the two
roadways built upon iron and stone piers;
the two land spans, which are nothing
more nor less than two Independent can
tilever bridges, and the suspension bridge,
which Is the main span supported by the
four big cables hanging over the towers.
It should be noted at this point that the
land spans of Brooklyn bridge are sup
ported In the same way as the central
span, by the cables, and are consequently
part and parcel of the bridge proper.
Comparing the vibration of the differ
ent parts of the Wllflomburg bridge, one
with the other, the Eagle man learned
that the roadways vibrate none at all, or
so Imperceptibly as to give only the very
slightest Indication by the Instrument
used. The central span vibrates to a
perceptible extent, but not to a notice
able one. The cantilever land spans vi
brate at least three or four times as
much.
Compared with the Brooklyn bridge,
the central span of the new bridge vi
brates, under present conditions, about
one-half as much. The land spans of the
Williamsburg bridge, under much smaller
strain, vibrate nearly twice as much as
does any part of Brooklyn bridge.
With these observations and facts the
Eagle reporter went to see Chief Engin
eer Nichols. Mr. Nichols not being at
the office, he was referred to Engineer
Robinson. Who was In charge of the con
struction pf the Williamsburg bridge for
several monthR during the last fall and
Winter, Mr. Robinson fin'd;
“,.o one need feel the slightest alarm
at the safety of the new bridge. I can
say from personal observation that the
structure Is exactly as It was Intended to ]
be In every particular. There Is a no
ticeable vibration in the two cantilever
spans. They would not be safe If this ,
vibration were absent. It Is the rule of ,
all cantilever structures that they show ,
a tendency to vibrate. They are built ,
In that way. The very fact that they are (
constructed on « counterbalance prlnci- |
pie, without being rigidly fixed, con- |
tributes to their vibration. This Is as It |
should be. The land spans of the Wil
liamsburg bridge have no organic rela
tion to the bridge proper.
"In the central span a different system
oi stiffening the truss Is used from that
pit ployed on the Brooklyn bridge. I feel
no hesitation In saying It Is a better one.
Of course, the bridge has not yet been
put to the test of having the cars run
over It. but I can see no possible reason
to doubt that such test, when It does
come, will show that It Is more rigid.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86090528/1916-05-23/ed-1/seq-8/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>BROOKLYN BRIDGE IS
33 YEARS OLD TODAY
.in u
By 1'nited Press.
New York, May 23. Brooklyn-
bridge is S3 years old to
day. It has brought the city
about $25,000,000 worth of rev.
enue In nickels in that time.
Since other bridges like it have
been opened, the revenue Las
not been so great. There are
now so many bridges like
Brooklyn bridge that it has to
be singled out for the curious
stranger in New York.
"Always worth the money."
Special feature tonight.</text>
	  </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
  <!This Marks the start of Topic #3.>
  <!Topic: Cocaine Crisis (1898 - 1915)>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-cocaine</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85042461/1898-12-11/ed-1/seq-10/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE COCAINE MONSTER
THROWING HIS TENTACLES
AROUND THE NATION
HOW IT GRIPS ITS VICTIMS
The Deadly Drug Whose Influence
Carries Men to Insanity and
Death Becoming Too Popular
Value of cocaine leaves imported at the
port of New York in 1894.114,384; imported
in 1807, #54.122; indicated value ot imports
for 18SKS, $75,000.
In these simple figures are contained the
elements of a warning sermon that would
startle all America. We seem to be rapidly
becoming a nation of cocaine fiends, it the
number of those addicted to the u.-e ol the
dreadful drug continues to increase at the
present rate the importation of what "as
originally regarded its a blessed alleviator
of pain will have to be classed with opium
ami its use prohibited by law, except tor
medicinal purposes.
At present the cocaine Bend can pill-chase
the drug without trouble and the case with
which it is taken is a fatal recommenda
tion to those who crave a nerve-dcadener.
No laborious cooking of pills over a lamp,
cleaning of implements or troublesome neces
sity for secrecy, as with the use of opium.
Cocaine can be taken at any time, with
scarcely any trouble, anil without a soul
besides the being aware ot his being
in the toils.
At first, that is. It will not be long before
every intimate friend will observe c change,
a gradual ami scarcely perceptible change,
come over the appearance and general con
duct of the cocaine fiend. II the one who
yields to the toxic influence of the drug be
a lawyer, then it will be noticed that Ilia
language as he pleads a case in court has
become particularly diffuse, while his argu
ments are long drawn out and lacking in
logic. Others will notice this peculiarity
and wonder. The victim will be in hli'siul
ignorance of anything wrong, for another
queer phase of the progress ot cocaine pots-
Suing is that il lulls the user into a de
lightful feeling of self-satisfaction, and,
whatever his shortcomings, he is contented
ami happy—until the influence of the drug
departs and leaves him only with the dead
ly craving for more that none can tight oil.
The lecturer who becomes a victim to the
cocaine habit will, to the surprise ot his
audience, spend the enure period allotted
to a certain subject on a single insignificant
part of it, or seem to tot get the topic en
tirely and wander into something entirely
foreign. It will strike the listeners that
the learned lecturer has been drinking or is
beginning lo get feeble-minded, there will
be nothing in lie appearance or manner of
the speaker to indicate that he himself has
the slightest knowledge that he lias not
been treating the subject in the brightest
and most careful way. Cocaine is a drug
that deludes its victims. It i- the very devil
blmsell in tin form of an innocent-looking
crystal, and the way the much-to-be-pitied
cocaine user is dragged slowly, but with
aw ml certainty, down, toinsanitsand death
is a terrible tribute to the strength ol the
demon that links in ihe drug.
This confusion oi ideas and language is
the first symptom of the toxic influence of
the cocaine beginning lo work. It you have
a friend in whom these symptoms are no
ticed, il might be well to find out il he is
addicted 10 the use of cocaine, tor at this
early stage the habit may be broken. Later
it is almost hopeless for the victim to try
to sunder his chains.
Begun in many cases in a legitimate way,
as an anesthetic, the surprisingly pleasant
effect is sought, lor again by the one who has
had a glimpse ai Ihe portals of elysium. This i
is tbe beginning of the terrible habit. The i
effect is a sense of exhilaration followed by a
quiet, dreamy state that causes the worried
man to forget his troubles and the sufferer i
his pain. nn,.,. this freedom from physical
and mental sickness has been experienced,
the cocaine fiend will t 01. or kill to get the I
ding. Enforced non-use of it will not cure
the victim. Sentence him to a term ot'im
prisonment, ami he will go straight from
the jail door to the nearest drug store to
secure cocaine before he eats or sleeps. i
This, of course, cannot last. From an '
occcasional use of the drug to insatiable .
craving is the rational course of the cocaine 
fiend. From thence to the insane asylum i
anil the grave is a swift and easy descent. i
Facsimile of Signature and Sketch Drawn. From Life of the Former Secretary of State Whose Able Work Is
Attracting; (International Attention
NEW YORK. Dec. 7.—Now that Frank
!J. Gould, the younaest of the sons of Jay
(«juld, has reached his majority, thereby
under the terms of his father's will becom
t ing one of the executors and trustees of the
estate, it is expected that he will also soon
be elected to membership in the directorates
of the various Gould properties. His three
older brothers are on these boards, but each
has some interest to which he devotes his
special attention. Oeorgc .1. Gould is es
pecially active in the management of the
Mis-ouri Pacific system. Edwin looks after
In his fall from health to physical and
mental disintegration the cocaine fiend un
dergoes a terrible experience. When not in
the temporary heaven that the drug pro
vides, the victim is in the lowest depths of
an infeino. He is subject to apprehen
sions, delusions and hallucinations. He suf
fers from insomnia, anorexia and gastralgic
latins, dyspepsia, chronic palpitations and
wiil-paresis. He is a terror both to himself
and others. The life of the man is a living
death. He knows it, nnd with this know
ledge -taring him in the face, he rushes for
the drug nnd is happy for a brief perftd
under its influence. It is time something
were done to keep from this high-strung
nation a drug so deadly. Clear-minded
medical men have recommended its exclu
sion from the country, believing that its use
medicinally should be foregone rather than
that such a cursed temptation should be
placed in tbe way of weak humanity.
"What tbe real action of the drug is, and
how to counteract its influence, aie at pres
ent puzzling questions to the medical fra
ternity. A lending member of the profes
sion to whom these questions were put re
plied, alter careful consideration, as follows:
lis physiological action is practically un
known. As an analgesic, it is uniform in
its action, and this is due'to the suspension
of the physiologic functions of the sensory
cells which it comes in contact with. Be
yond this, it is an excitant of the cerebro
spinal axis, later it has a peculiar ac? Tun
on the encephalon, manifest in a wide range
of physical phenomena. Beyond this a
great variety of widely variable symptoms
appear. In some cases all the intellectual
faculties are excited to the highest degree.
In others a profound lowering of the senses
Hid functional activities occur. Morphine
takers can use large quantities of cocaine
.vithou. any bad symptoms. Alcoholics
ire also able to bear huge doses without
lunger. Not (infrequently the excitement!
taused by cocaine goes on to convulsions and
ieath. The morphine
and alcoholic inebriates very soon ecquire a
certain tolerance to targe doses taken at
once. The cocaine User takes large quan
tities but in small doses frequently repeated.
:He becomes frightened at the effects of
huge doses, and when be cannot get the
effects from small (to him safe) doses, he
resorts to alcohol, morphine or chloral. In
' many cases memories of the delusions and
hallucinations are so vivfd and distressing
i that other narcotics are used to prevent
their recurrence. In other cases the recol-
I lection is very confused ami vague, and
I strong suspicions rill tbe mind that the real
(condition is grossly exaggerated by the
friends for some deterring effect. In com
mon with opium and alcoholics there is
moral paralysis, untruthfulness and low
cunning m order to conceal and explain the
condition by other than the real causes.
The prognosis is always doubtful when the
addiction has continued any length ol tune.
The temporary removal of the drug and
restoration of the case occurs In nearly till
cases, but unless a radical change of life and
li\ ing is made, and the patient gives un
usual care to his health and to tbe avoidance
of every source of exhaustion of nerve and
brain, and every condition of peril to his
health, the danger of relapse is very prom
inent.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn87093039/1911-05-12/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>DANGERS Of DEADLY COCAINE
Rapid Increase of the Most rnsidioiis Drug
Habit—The Craving Usually Acquired by
Accident
With the month of May comes the
opening of the six months harvest of
the soda fountains. "What will you
have?" asks the amiable clerk and
points to a list of sirups, a row of gayly
colored bottles and some large bowls on
the counter containing crushed straw
berries, sliced pineapple and other
I tempting fruits. If you stick to the
fruit sirups and the fruit is really good,
no harm is done. On the contrary-
But if you turn to the bottled attrac
tions or listen to the promise of their
much advertised qualities, then beware.
Here is plain warning from Dr. L. F.
Kebler, chief of the division of drugs
in the government bureau of chemistry:
"Attention is directed to the danger of
soft drinks containing caSeine, extract
of kola nut and extract of coca leaf, the
active principle of the two latter being
cocaine."
According to Dr. Kebler, scores of
soft drinks, dangerously medicated, are
sold at soda water fountains as stimu
lating and refreshing summer drinks
without the slightest intimation to pur
chasers that their stimulating and re
freshing qualities come from cocaine, a
drug that produces one of the worst
habits known to the medical prefession.
"We have seen," said Dr. Kebler,
"how the opium habit may be acquired
by the use of various proprietary or se
cret preparations usually employed as
domestic remedies, and so the cocaine
habit may be developed by the use of
these much lauded soft drinks."
During a recent visit to Washington
I talked with two heads of departments
in the bureau of chemistry, both active
in government prosecutions of drugged
soda water sirups. "There is no ques
tion," said one of these authorities,
"that the presence of cocaine in soft
drinks tends to create in the consumer,
whether child or adult, a predisposition
towards the cocaine habit."
It is evident that the manufacturers
of these soft drink sirups have only one
motive for putting cocaine into them —
that is to make them popular, to make
them taste good, to make them sell
better. And this popularity, this pleas
ant taste and better sale come simply
and solely because there is enough co
caine in these soft drinks to give some
thing of the stimulating and exhilarat
ing effect that cocaine always gives.
"It is not uncommon," says Dr.
Kebler, "to find persons addicted to the
use of medicated soft drinks. It is a
well known fact that many factory em
ployes, stenographers, typewriters and
others subject to mental or nervous
strain spend a part of their earnings for
drinks of this character. Parents, as a
rule, withhold tea and coffee from their
children; but, having knowledge of the
presence of cocaine, caffeine or other
deleterious agents in soft drinks, they
unwittingly permit their children to be
harmed by their use."
Cocaine —what is it? The Standard
Dictionary tells us: "Cocaine, a white,
bitter, crystalline alkaloid contained in
coca leaves; used in medicine as a
local anesthetic." And again: "Coca,
the dried leaves of a South American
shrub of the flax family, used in medi
cine as a tonic; chewed by tne native i
Indians as a nervine stimulant." There
is no connection between the coca
shrub and the cocoa palm tree that pro
duces cocoa nuts.
An ounce containg 480 grains and a
grain of cocaine is a dose. From a
single source of cocaine supply in New
York city 480,000 doses of this dan
gerous drug were illegitimately dis
pensed every month.
How is the habit usually acquired?
"By accident, like other drug habits.
I'm sorry to say that one of these —er
—accidents is the presence of cocaine
in catarrh medicines." Dr. Podstata
proceeded to give me details in the
case of one of his patients, a man of 22,
who became a cocaine fiend quite inno
cently by taking a widely advertised
"catarrh cure" that contained only a
small percentage of cocaine, but, alas,
enough to establish the habit. The
young man sniffed his "catarrh cure"
up his nose, and after each sniffing ex
perienced a characteristic sense of ela
tion, a peculiar well being. He took
more and more of the stuff and soon
{discovered that his exhilaration came
from cocaine in the powder. Now, it
was cocaine he wanted, not the catarrh
cure; and presently he began to take
the drug pure, sniffing it, after the man-
i ncr of adepts and finally learning to use
jit in hypodermic injections. Soon he j
! learned that the sensations were not at I
all pleasant. Far from it! Quick after
each period of intoxication came the !
i dread of reaction that calls for more and i
always more cacaine. The character
istic physical and moral deterioration
went on rapidly. The victim grew sal
low-faced, sunken-eyed, restless, irrita
ble. He lost ambition and persever
ance. He became a liar, a wreck, help
less and useless, and within a year he
was placed in an asylum.
Notice that all this came to pass be
cause a perfectly well-meaning young
man bought at a reputable drug store
in Chicago what was advertised as an j
excellent cure for catarrh. And before
he knew what he was doing and taking |
he had become a "coke fiend" and his
life was irretrievably ruined.
At Hull House, that haven of good
works in Chicago, I found impressive
corroboration of the statement that chil
dren easily fall into the cocaine habit.
Dr. Hamilton, a woman bacteriologist
of Hull House, made an investigation
among boys and young men in the
neighborhood and found that numbers
of them were regular users of the drug.
Dr. Hamilton found that the cocaine
habit had spread through one group of
seven boys. The youngest,Willie, was
coming home from school one day when
a negro who offered him a sniff of pow
der, saying it would make him feel
good. Willie sniffed the powder and,
as he expressed it, felt like a million
aire. The negro sold him what was
lelt of the powder in a little pill box
for IS or 20 cents, and told the boy he
would be around that corner every even
ing with more of the stuff. He also
suggested that Willie inform his boy
friends of the wonderful effects of this
powder. ' Willie went back to the cor
ner and bought more of the drug. He
wanted to feel like a millionaire. He
told his two brothers, young men of 17
and 18, and they tried the powder.
One by one four of their friends were
initiated until the group of seven was
formed. All seven became absolutely
demoralized; they quit going to school,
stopped work, stayed away from home
all night, going on regular cocaine de
bauches and spending as much as $7
in a single day for the drug. When
their money gave out they would pawn
their clothes, they would steal, they
would do anything to get more money
to buy more cocaine.
Through the earnest efforts of the
Hull House people these seven boys
were cured of the habit. Dr. Hamilton
thinks a cure is possible for the young,
though rarely possible for adults. Even
so, the effects of their long indulgence
in cocaine did them permanent injury.
Their power of resistence was enfeebled
and three of them died of tuberculosis.
It is a question, too, whether the others
have been quite sound mentally.
I talked with a husband and wife,
both "coke fiends," whom I found in
a filthy hovel on "Cocaine alley," the ,
foulest part of Chicago, and they both j
assured me that they thought nothing
of spending 84 or 85 a day for "dope." j
They might lack food, clothing, warmth,
decency, everything; but without co
caine they could not and would not
live. This husband, strange to say,
was a man of intelligence and nice in
stincts. He wore glasses and had a
fine brow. He was a carpenter by trade
able to earn good wages until he got
this habit. His wife, a shattered, shriv
eled, frantic creature (she was on the
verge of the cocaine "leaps" ), informed
me with a certain pride that she had
once been a famous dancer in the Black
Crook company.
In an adjoining hovel was a colored
—a tall, lithe, wild-eyed victim, who
said a dollar's worth of cocaine was only
enough for a few sniffs, it would scarcely
last an hour.
Pure cocaine, which is manufactured
freely in various cities, is worth about
84 an ounce. That is what crooked
cocaine merchants pay for it. Then he
retails the drug by the little pink pill
box full, or the little blue bottle full,
and by thus subdividing it gets for each
ounce 820 or 825. That is, when he
sells the stuff pure to those who want it
for "hypos" and know the difference;
but to the "sniffers" he sells the drug
half adulterated with acetanilid, a very
cheap powder that looks like cocaine,
and allows him to double his gain.
I Sometimes these vulture retailers will
| work off on very desperate, half-crazed
! "fiends" a quality of "dope" that is
two-thirds adulteration, which gives the
dealers a profit of 860 an ounce!
No wonder a flashily-dressed negTO,
known as the "coke king of Chicago."
i boasted that, if the police would leave
I him alone for a single year, he would j
retire with a fortune. And no wonder
Ihe has been able, by the devices of
| well paid lawyers, to get himself speedily
out of the Bridewell every time he has!
been sentenced there. Residents on j
the mean street where this nogro lives I
will tell you of smart automobiles draw
ing up before his close-barred, dingy
shanty, and of well-dressed men or veiled I
j women hurrying through the alley to a
1 back door. They knock and the door
I opens slightly. The caller deposits a ■
coin in the hand that appears in the
i opening and receives in return a small
: box of cocaine. A chain guard pre
vents the caller forcing the door open
| more than a few inches. It is always j
quite a trick, the detectives say, to
I "catch these cocaine dealers with the
goods."</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1912-12-04/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE COCAINE TRAFFIC. i easy matter to get the evldence against
cocaine sellera?when he told how he
\ had taken a ahort tlme to get a 
j qualnted with the drug users in her
' neighhorhood and had then been able
: to bny It from Mrs. Fisher with their
introduction.
District Attorney Cropaey began hia
j iidive pursult of the cocaine sellers by
Interesting Deputy Commissioner
i Walsh in the matter. They intend to
' keep after these lllegal merchants un
| til they dean up Brooklyn.
? We have already recelved reports
: from wholesale houses that the sale of
the drug has been greatly redu. ed,"
naid Mr. t'ropsey yesterday, "and lt is
eartaJa that our flfty-elght convictlotiH
have stirred up the tranVkers in co?
caine ao that many of them are giving
lt up as a bad Job to taekie in Brook?
lyn."
Urgea More Draatic Penalty.
The District Attorney of King*
County belleves the law should be
made more drastlc, but declures re
sults ii.ay eaelly be obttalned under
the present law lf the police actually
do the work they are supposed to do.
"I belleve that an amendment mak
lng the poasesston of cocaine, without
n physl'ian'H preacription, a felony ln
itself, without Inslstlng that the prose
cution prove the possessor Intended to
MU lt, would be a good addltion to the
lnw. and I belleve the punlshment
should be lncreased from the present
llmlt of one year's lmprlaonment to
something like flve years," he said.
Mr. Cropsey thought that prison sen
tences of some length were probably of
more ubc ln curlng the vtctlms of the
cocaine habit than any other possible
retnedy.
ln this connectlon the fsct standsout
that one of the chlef things prison
keepers have to contend with ln carlng
for their prlsonera ls to keep them from
obtalnli.g cocaine. Bo prevalent Is this
habit among criminals that cocaine
has even been sent bllndly Into filng
Sing prison by outslders without any
knowledge that lt would reach their
own frlends wlthln.
Warden Kenncdy, of Sing Sing. told
a Tribune reporter re ently that on one
occaslon he had bought a few eamp
. halrs neoeasary for extra a**ats In the
ehapel. and though the transactlon was
handled entlrely by the prison authorl
ties. he thought of the poaslbillty of
cocaine smuggllng, and had the chalrs
carefully examlned on arrlval.
Ha found each chair had had n smnll
hole bored iu the woodwork. whleh had
b.-en filled with cocaine. then carefully
covercil up nnd vnrnished over. Inves
tlgatlon ea to the source of this pros
paettVO gift to the OOC-Joa users iii th?*
prison had led nowliere, because the
dealer who supplled the chalra could
ot flnd at. what Btage of their handling
the drug bad been hldden.
Tlv warden aald hla guards had
found cocaine hldden In the backa of
ii alr brushes sent to convlets by friends
OOtBlda. They had found lt even on
poatenrda. where lt had been hldden in
minute quantitlee under the stamp; in
the mlddle of clgarettes sent In to mn
victs, and even ln the hatbanda jf
visitors who came to see them.
l'ractically the same condltlona are
true ln the prlaona on Blackwell's Isl?
and, and even in the TombB, where
men are not conflned for long periods.
Taft Urgaa Congresa to Aet.
The world-wlde peril in the growth
of cocaine, oplum and other drug
habit*, which was the reason for the
calllng of a apeclal internatlonal con?
ference on the aubject at The Hague
last summer, recelved promlnent men
tion ln Prealdent Taft's message to
Congress yesterday. Bills are In pros
pect in the preaent Congress over which
both State and Treasury departments
hav worked. and which will probably,
aui.ng oth-r tbinge, put a ,_.-k to iu-1
Idruggists denounce
j cocaine law laxity. There can be no question of the need
of the most severe restrlctlon of the sale
of cocaine. The retall pharmacists w?re
th? first to rcallxaj the need of restrktloP
on the sale of hablt-formlng drugs. I
lntroduced a resolution at the 8t. Louis
meeting of the American Pharmaceutlcal
Association, ln 1901. provldlng for the ?;
polnfment of a commlttee to considcr tbfl
uuestlon of the acqulrement of drug
baMtfl and the best niethods of legislatlvo
regulatlon of the dunger. Furmerly the exertitlon of the cocaine
laa v..i* under the Board of Phannacy.
and when we held the power we? dflBD?l
the rMaton out. B-it now the board has
nothing to d?> wlth the matter.
? We agreed to the amendment making
the poOflflflflbM of the drug without a
dOOtOffl prescription a felony, because It
?BflOMd an If tli.it was a more effectlve
method Of reachlng the seller who trled
to p.iss himself off n_ a us> r of the drug.
I'lithr tbal amendment thfl druggist ls
roqalrfld to flll out a cocaine sale certlfi
rate, and lf any one Is OBBgM wlth 10
eaJBfl OB his person without one of thes*.
i certltlcates be Is llable to $.V?D line or one
year's imprisonma-nt, or both.
Hintt at Cocaine Oraft.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1912-12-06/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>BOSTON IN COCAINE WAR
Dance Halls Make "Fiends" of
Schoolgirls?Two Arrests.
Boston. Dee. 5? The revelatlon that
young alrle. aoma not yet out of aehool,
ara belng made "drug flenda" through
cheap dance halls and men who haunt
tham felllng cocaine has stlrred the
pollce to a vlforous campaign.
Two men were sentenced ln the munlcl
pal court for aalllng cocaine lllegally
Their arreats were the flrst of a aerlea
whieh tha poliee plau to make. Father Flynn haa been an ardent
worker against the Insldloua growth of
the cocaine traffic in hia pariah, and hia
campaign haa dleclosed to him that the
agents who promote it have not
scrupled to create a demand for It
among children between thlrteen and
seventeen years old.
"I know of at least 100 children be?
tween thlrteen and seventeen years old,"
said Father Flynn, "who have been
habltual cocaine or heroin users. They
cven rarry it into their schoolrooma,
concealed in hollow penclla and watch
cases. and, in Bome inatancea, in fake
handages which were wrapped around
suppoaed cuts on their flngers."
The clergyman said that he had no
douht whatever but that the coacaine
sellera. eapeclally those who sold the
drng to young girls, were in league
with the agenta of the "white alave"
traffic. he said, "and I
belleve that the agents of the 'white
ala\e' traffic are behind the cocaine
trafflC Hanglng is too good for theae
wre'ches. Qod help the poor souls too
weak and the young mlnds too frail te
grasp the terrlble meanlng of thia habit
and its awful conaequences."
Father Flynn has organlied a boys'
club ln his parish on non-dcnomina
tional llnes whlch now has three hun
dred members. Every one of theae
young fellows Is pledged to report to
Fhthcr Flynn cven the most apparently
trlfiing suaplclous clrcumatances which
he observes along the linc of cocaine
selllng. Cocaine ia being aold in randy atore.
and small frult atores as well aa drurc
atores in the Brownsville section, Fa?
ther Flynn said, and it will take the
most vlgoroua klnd of a campaign to
eradlcate it. 'COKE' VENDER C0NV1CTED
Oaught After He Had Oauied
Indictment of Another.
John Callinan, a vhtim of the cocaine
hablt, who tas insttumental In obtalnlng
etldaate Of cocaine s'-lling agaliiFt Dft
Abiaham A. I*vy, was convloted of .*>n
attempt to apll cocaine yesterday befor*
Judge O'Sullk-an In (leneral gesaiona. Jle
was remandU untll Monday for aei.ten.e.
Judfe O'Sullhan aald that he hoped thi
law would Mun be amended ao that
uiers of the drug could be dealt with
properly.
"I regret." aald Judge O'Sulllvan. "thut
the law at present ia not framed io that
we can aultably punlah auch men aa >ou
and at th* lame time protect the people
of the atate I truat that th* law *tll
f-oon be amended."
Callinan waa arrested on B*pt*mber A
last ln a bllllard room at No. 2269 8eond
avenne with fmr other men. Opium and
cocaine were ftund on the prlsoneis, and
in their search for more of the druga tlie
detectlves who made the rald rlpped off
the baaeboard. Beneath It they found
two revolvers, i aandbag. a stlletto and
more opium.
Callinan was ronvlcted of the sam* of
fence ln 1*10 and tentenced to four months
in the penltentlary. In June, 1J?12, he waa
agaln arrested for havlng cocaine ln his
possesslon. He told James A. Delehanty,
an Aaaistant Diatrlct Aitorney, at that
tlm* that he waa not a "coke ttend" and
that he would break hlmself of the hablt.
He alao offered to glve whst help he
mlght toward the arrest and convlctlon
of cocaine sellera.
With Detectlve Dltseh, of Police Head
quartera. and Inspeetors from the Board
of Health, h* called on Dr. Abraham A.
lArvy and, lt ia alleged, bought a quan
tlty of cocaine frqm Dr. Levy wlthout a
preacrlptlon and gave him marked billa
in payment therefor. Dr. I.?vy 1s now
under indictment. and his caae 'a con
*lderrd by the Diatrlct Attorney to be
the atrongeat that has been prepared
agalnat a vender of cocaine aince the law
was amended.
OEMOCRAT8 LEFT $373 UNSPENT.
Washlngton, Dec. I -The atatement of
recelpts and expendlturea of the Deino
cratk Natlonal Congreas Commlttee
ahowa $12,?45 ln contributlona, nioatly In
small amounta. and a balance on hand of
tm. The Weatern branch ot the com?
mlttee reportcd t2S,2M |n contributlona
aad t2t,Mf iu expendlturea.
COCAINE BROUGHT IN
BY STR1KE BREAKERS
Former Chief City Food Inspector Says Cuban
Negroes Intiroduced the Vice in
New York.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030272/1914-02-15/ed-1/seq-29/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Drug dealers have
grown prosperous
on this type.
With Practically
Unrest ricted
Traffic Cocaine
Vice Has Grown
So Swiftly That
We Are Most
Drugged Nation in
World With 4.45
Per Cent, of Popu
lar on Addicted to
Habit
Hitting the Pipe."
Tons of opium im
ported for "medicinal
purposes" are used
for this purpose.
Campaign Under
taken by Mrs. Will
iam K. Vanderbilt,
Sr., for Extermina
tion of Practice One
of the Greatest
Moral Struggles in
History Cocaine
and Heroin Dead-
?k lies t of Habit Form. The commerce in cocaine, heroin, mor
pliiin im opium now approximates the opium traffic
of i 'n n China history's most notorious example
of .i I, -god nation when after 200 years of its com-
opiurn 0.5 per cent, of China's population
id to be opium smokers. With tho aid of
,y every civilized nation in tho world China
v reduced that figure to 4.1 per cent., while
d States twenty years of practically un
. traffic in drugs has made drug addicts
'ent. of tho population.  but u sniff of cocaine after
lifting Its victim into a half hour's losy overestima
tion drops him into tho streets and alleys in a state
of dangerous melancholia. So brief is the drug's
effect that it ta' es from i to $! u day to satisfy a
cocaine addict more nion y lian any other" drug
addiction exacts, That's why "coke" produces more
criminals in the city of New York than any other
single cause.
No other country in tho world knows the cocaine
habit. "Cocaine addiction is an American habit,"
says Dr. Charles U. Towns of 110 West Kighty-first
street, a recognized authority. "It is tho result of
our high pressure of living, our craving for over
stimulation, our proiienoss to 'take something' when
wo don't feel well. I have never known an Italian, a
Hungarian, a Itussiau, a Pole and only a few Jews
(except in the underworld) who took drugs."
"Cocaine addiction is the easiest habit to acquire
and the hudest to cure," say- Dr. PoiNtata, a Chi
engo drug expert. "Nothitur so iii kly deteriorate
its victim or provides o short a cut to the in-ano
asylum," says Dr. Towns, liccnu-c it takes such a
liiick, deadly grip of its victim then- ate some physi
cians who refuse to ndmini-tcr any cocaine what
ever', even ill legitimate medical piuctiee , Yet any
crook can bring a carload of cocaine fiom Philadel
phia into New York city, and the Interstate Com
merce Commirsion is owerless to interfere.
Notwithstanding its vitiating effects the growth
of cocaine add.etiou is indicated by the i:tc, easing
import into the United States of coca leaves, the
only source of cocaine and tin product of a shrub
which cannot be grown here. According to t e
American Pharmaceutical Association the oca iri
Iort from l.S'JS to 11102 inclusive was valued at fM.'.'l 1,
from lWO to 1007, inclusive, $1.11111 liini. The ;r - it
annual cousin ptiou of cocaine i L'nn.nno u ce-. , ,
which 02 per cent, is used illegitimately ior 1 ve.y
man, woman and child in the United State-, a s '.'
of cocaino sufficiently strong to kill -evera! m d.i"
Its enormous profit explains the growth of t'.e
cocaine business. An ounce of cocaine, wholes... ,
costs about $1. Divided into pink pill boxes 111, d I
bottles the ounce is sold without adulteration l"r
from $20 to to tho-e who use the needle and ki on
tho difference. Adulterated heavily wit iicetani'..!
it is sold to "sniffers" lor from J into $v 1 ounce and
half crazed fiends on the verge of the "1 u nine leap-"
can be made to yield even gi eater piolit. Thus
profits ranging from .VX) to i,.VM per cent, on the
investment have entrenched the cocaine business
011 a nationwide scale.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030272/1914-02-15/ed-1/seq-30/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The widespread net' of cocaine In
tlie comparatively short period of
time since It.i discovery," sas J)r.
Towns, "has been brought about by
patent preparations coutalr'ng small
quantities of II."
During Its tlrst few years cocaine nd
illction spread through the wld" soli' of
"catarrh cures." which contained from 2
to 4 per cent, of cocaine. These "cures,"
according to Samuel Hopkins Ad. mis In
Ciilliri'i UVi'Afjr, were "Dr. Ilirncys Ca
tarrh Cure," "Dr. Colo's Catarrh Cure."
"Dr. Agnow's Caiairh Powder" and
"Crown t 'atari li Powder." Not only did
these "euro." Introduce many pcions
Into depth of cocaine addiction, but
they pointed the way to a method of j
taking cocaine easier than by hypo- 1
dermic. Among the thousands who contracted
cocaine addiction through the innocent
putchase of a patent medicine was Mrs,
Anna ('. .Meyers, who was prominent
socially In Chicago and In lsim was a
member of the board of managers of
the Chlcngo World's Fair. In a confes
siou detailing the career of crime Into
which cocaine plunged her Mrs. Meyers
Mays: "I used to get the little boxes of
the drug and call it 'my baby' and 'my
only friend,' cry over It and laugh and
dance like an Insane person." Crothers of Hartford, Conn., "begin the
use of cocaine that they may whip their
Inventiveness to action."
Walters in restaurants use drugs to
quicken their memory. It has been
estimated that 1." per cent, of all the
medical men in the United States are
drug addicts, "One
half of nil my drug
patients ore physi
cians," says Dr.
Towns, who has u
hill now pending at
Albany, Introduced
by Senator John .1.
Itoylan, barring all
drug addicted phy
sicians from prac
tice. School chil
dren, even ut the
ages of 7 and N. are
offered cocnlne nnd
horoln by pedlors
about public school
buildings. The Hull
House campaign of
l'.io.l started with
the disc ivery thai
certain negroes in
Chicago Were stop
ping school chil
dren on the tilde
walks and selling
them a penny Ixoc
of the deadliest
habit forming drug
In the world and
asking them to "tell
all their Hi t I e
friends about It "
In that sect Inn
of civilized society
known as the under.
World cocaine ad
diction Is practically
universal Cnderlts
Intluetice ate most of
the daring crimes
committed. ' Most of
the attacks tiMin
white women of the
South." says Dr
Christopher Koch
"are the tilled re
suit of a cocaine
crazed negro brain "
Thousands of dingy
hovels are scattered
tllloliuli ttle negro
sections of Southern
cities where "snow"
is retailed In dime
boxes through back
doors which are
prevented by chains
from opening more
than three Indies
District Attor
ney St. Clair estl
m. les that In New
Orleans nlone there
nie 2.1,000 negro
I calne addicts who
p a t r o n i ze these
I Joints, Overseers of
Southern labor have
been known to put
cocaine Into their
gang's rations in order to get more
work out of them.
As a result of the wide cocaine addic
tion among negroes in the South Au
gust llrahni cites figures to show that
the negro race, which forms lu.T per
cent, of the nation's population, com
mits 37.12 per cent, of the murders.
.1. IMgar llrown of Chicago Is authority
for thij statement that the murder rate
of Germany is three per l.opo.ooo Inhabi
tants and of Canada live per 1.U0O.0UO.
Here are the 1911 murder rates of six
Southern cities: Memphis, Tenn.. 3!
per l.iHHi.itoa, Charleston, S. C 423;
Savannah. nu 378; Nashville. Tenn.,
3:.3. Atlanta Ca 29R; New Orleans,
211. Manhattan and The llronx. Its derivatives, heroin and codeine,
il.."o to 3 an ounce; cocaine, II. ."u to
12 an ounce; coca leaves, 5 cents to 10
i cuts a pound.
The effect of a tariff Increase In abat
ing the Importation t.f these drugs may
lie seen In these tlgllles; The Payne
tariff on August .'i, U'i'9. raised the duty
on cocaine from 2.", per cent, ad valorem
to 11.50 an ounce, and the cocaine Im
port Jumped fr 111 32.272 ounces III 19I
to .H,."i',o ounces In 1910. It took coca
leaves off the free list and Imposed a
duty of a cents a pound, and the coca
iiiiiioit iunniid from 7os.o IC pounds in
1VI0 to 1,2211, 771. .I pounds in 19)1. He bought 9,3110 ounces of
cocaine between December 9, 19a. and
January 30, 1913, although thousands of
doctors use less than one ounce In a
lifetime. I tut this was perfectly legal.
It was Dr. lllcksielu's opium Indiscre
tions which sent him to the Federal
pcuileiitliil'y. Assistant District Attor
ney Floyd W'llmot has under present
surveillance a West Side dm lor who has
200 legal customers to whom he sells
legally thirty-one half grain tablets of
cocaine for Ml centH. Not until
last year did the House pass a measure
i the Senate has not acted on It yet) re
quiring every person who distributes
men leaves to leglster his name with
the colleitor of Internal revenue and to
pay a lax of a dollar a year, further,
prohibiting the selling of cocaine except
on a pun (laser's order to b- kept for two
years, accessible to Federal and State
authorities. Any unregistered person
transporting cocaine fiom State to State
or having It In his itossessbm s made
liable to a 2,0on line or Imprisonment
not to exceed the years, or both.
The same bill furthermore prohibits
the export of opium, raises the Internal
leveiiue tn.x on smoking opium from lia
COCAINE'S DEADLY ACTION.
The itJhttiny erpcricner shova Mr dradtinrB of the iriif uicaw i .
rat'ric mldid who the mrdlc often consume Hrentv (train of the dr , ,(,,,,
thin record the cffict of one grain on a man vho had never tahn ii ljmi
It tea an experiment pcrformid by Dr. .. Novell Wan, recorded in th, Sull,
cat Xeir" of ISS and widely quoted at that time, ft tra an open qui ti ,nf
doctor then a to whether cocaine wa or wa not dangerous.
At 6 P. M. I injected one-quarter grain of Squlbb's cocaine under the s jn
of my forearm.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn90059228/1914-06-03/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Clergyman Declares Cocaine Can BeWis.,,
Bought as Easily as Ice Cream and [.last Saturday.
Asserts That A States Should Have
Uniform LawsTells of Effect of
Drug on Victims.
Hew York."There Is only one way
to pat an end to the cocaine traffic in
the United States, and that is to pass
a comprehensive federal law which
will regulate the sale, net only ef the
harmful and obnoxious cocaine, but all
drugs and narcotics that have vitiat
ing qualities," aafd the Rev. James
B. Curry of St. James' Soman Cotholie
church when asked for his views on
the war on habit forming drugs.
Father Curry became interested in
the fight on cocaine nine years ago, and
he has been fighting it ever since. He
is familiar with every phase of the
matter
"It is a matter that the federal gov
ernment mast deal with sooner or
later,' he said. "The widespread use
of drop*, which is ruining the lives of
thousands of men and women in this
country and. most important of all.
lives of thousands of boys and girls,
makes it incumbent on the officials in
Washington to take cognizance of this
serious matter The time for procras
tination is past, and we must get quick
action. 'On some sides I have heard physi
cians of this city criticised for filling
prescriptions which enable the bearer*
to obtain supplier of cocaine Rput
bie physicians ore striving to lessen
this evil to the best of their ability
"I do think the wholesale drug
houses are responsible for the spread
ef this evil As an example of how
easy it is to obtain cocaine and other
harmful drugs from wholesale bouses,
an acquaintance of mine recently in
formed me that he could jret as much
of the drag as be wanted without an
order from a physician or anybody
ifise I aSBL"* surprised that I re-1
raestet him ttPmafce the effort.
"He made out a list and mailed it to
a drug bouse and asked for prices. In
eluded In the list was cocaine In a
few days he received the list with the
prices filled in, and. checking off some*
of the drugs, including cocaine, he re
mailed the list Not long after that
the goods were delivered, and the co
eaine was in the order. It was as
easy as buying ice cream. Some persons have asked me where
the cocaine habit originally came from.
It is a hard question to answer, hut I
really think that it came from the
West Indies imagine that the negro?
help on ships from the West Indies
brought the habit to New York years
ago."</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85058396/1914-06-06/ed-1/seq-20/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Mrs Vanderbilt began her fight
on the nation-wide use of drugs in
the New York Legislature, where
she fought for a bill prohibiting tho
sale of cocaine, heroin and mor
phine. She has given large sums of
money to organizations opposing the
drug habit In her efforts to obtain
legislation against its sale
The entire civilized world has
been shouting about the horrors of
the opium traffic of China. In America, however; the use of
the drug is on the Increase.
Laws preventing the transporta
tion of cocaine from one State to
another are sought by Mrs. Van
derbilt, and in working for federal
laws her experts have compiled
data to show the enormity of the
drug habit. Drugs are used by all classes. The
criminal class Is addicted to Its use.
Cocaine 1b Injected Into the aim.
Opium la smoked and taken in oth
er ways. Sometimes the drugs are
snuffed. They are taken to drive
away tho feeling of drowsiness
sometimes. Country doctors ac
quire the drug habit because of
their long hours of work. They
take drugs to keep themselves
awake and take other drugs so they
! can go to Bleep quickly.  In 1888 Dr. J. Howell
Way wrote to the Medical News his
experiences with cocaine.
He Bald he Injected, one-quarter
1 grain of cocaine in his forearm at
j 6 p. m. Thirty minutee later he
took a half grain. In ten minutes
he became restless and his hreath
lng was affected. In twenty min
utes his pupils began to dilate.
By 7 20 his condition was near
collapse. By 7:30 he began to fear
he would die. Cocaine was not as
well known then as it is now. and
Dr. Way took the drug simply as
an experiment. In America, drug
iis rs quickly lake to cocaine and
heroin. The drug causes the user
to turn criminal and to die. Five
years Is tho average life of tho
cocaine fiend. ,
No other vice renders its victim
so dangerous. Opium, morphine
and hasheesh -end their victims
searching for solitude, but a sniff of
cocaine. sftfr llftlne its victim into
ITPPER left Mrs. YV. K.
Vanderbilt. Upper
right A victim of the co
caine habit, after receiving
an injection in his arm. Cen
ter Dream of the drug
merchant, getting money
from his victims. Below
Scene in a drug cafe.
a half hour's rosy overestlmatlon.
drops him into the streets and al
les In a state of dangerous mel
ancholia. So brief is the drug's ef
fect that it takes from $4 to $5 a
day to satisfy a cocaine addict.
"Cocaine addiction Is the easiest
habit to acquire and the hardest to
cure."</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85058396/1915-05-22/ed-1/seq-15/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>In several courts men and worn
en found guilty of selling cocaine
have been given six months in jail,
while under the state laws they re
ceived no more than a 950 fine fr
their offense. The $f.o was paid by
the politician or drug vender and
all was over as far as the courts
were concerned, although the per
son arrested man or woman prat
beaten almost into Insensibility bj
the drug-vender and other friends
when he or she returned to the
colony. In fact,
II Is ibe intention of the United
States government to go more deep
ly intc these matters and ferret out
nol the poor unfortunates Who sell
cocaine for commission of the
drug itself, but the real persona
who make ihe profit.
The Federal courts are nirl. Qg
out Jail sentences to the small of
fenders, but when the internal rev
enue agents get to the real sellers
of cocaine the men who make a
great profit from the misfortunes of
their brothers there will be sen
tences of not less than five years
in the Federal penitentiary, It is
said. The smaller offenders are the men
and women who sell the dine lor
their master, the man in control of
ihe supply, for a commission on
drugs. They work and slave for
him and he owns them body and
soul by his payment of a small box
of cocaine or a few morphine tab
lets. The man In control Is all the
more heartless In that he is not a
user of the drugs himself, (such a
man might be in sympathy with oth
er stricken creatures) but is wise
enough to let it alone and profit by
their experiences.
In a recent raid of opium joints
and lairs of the users of morphine
and cocaine. Col. L. G N'utt. in
Charge of the eastern division of
Missouri and one of the most effl-
A TYPICAL. ALLELE WHERE "DOPC FIEND5" THRIVE.. I
cient and experienced internal rev
enue agents in the country, found
hundreds of unfortunates under the
influence of drugs. In St. Louis his men under h's dl-
rection arrested Henry Wilsmatf
the so-called "Cocaine King." This
man. kuown as "Wig Henry. " and
having served a penitentiary sen
tence for slaying "Red" Tremalne,
the laBt "cocaine king," is alleged to
have been selling the drugs to a
colony of cocaine and morphine
users in a miserable row of tene
ments nearby a structure known as
Filipino Row, and so filthy and foul
that no human being, unless under
the Influence of drugs, would live
there
There were men and women of all
types found there.  She lives in a
basement hovel of one of h'i own
buildings and Is in fear of ihe death
that she knows the cocaine-nends
will metS out to her some day. She
has money and she thinks that some
night some maddened drug user will
rome to her miserable dwelling ana
murder her for her money.
In all of (he misery and filth that
surround her, she is not more mis
erable ihan the unfortunates who
pay hf r for the renl of their squalid
one-room dwellings, and pay glnd
ly so that thev may be near their
source of supply of the orugs.
HON Till Y
EXIST. Her energy then, excited
under the Influence of drugs, was at
such a pitch that she easily could
earn enough money for tomorrow's
cocaine
she and others lived this same life
day after day working far into lho
night to buy cocaine and then
m Jmg the greutvr part of the day
in recovering from Ms effects.</text>
	  </result>
	  <!This marks the start of the additional 10 documents for Topic #3>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1914-03-10/ed-1/seq-9/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Sniff! Sniff!
The cocaine is up- his nostrils. He
"feels better."- '
Quickly he rubs his upper lip clean,
brushes off his coat, and goes on with
his work. No one has seen him. For
a little while he will be all right
Then torture will begin to creep upon
him, only to be appeased by another
recourse to the "dope."
That is the beginning of the mov
ing picture, play, "The Drug Terror,"
in which the horrors of cocaine and
heroin will be presented in their most
graphic form - to movie audiences
throughout the United States.
The story is that of a shipping
clerk in a wholesale drug house, who,
lured by the enormous profits that
are offered, becomes a trafficker in
cocaine and heroin. His business has
many branches. He supplies ped
dlers who sell "doped" candy to
school children. Agents of his con
duct flower stands, where working
girls buy nosegays powdered with cocaine.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn87093039/1911-05-12/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>DANGERS OF DEADLY COCAINE. In my opinion," writes one of the
workers in the Philadelphia cocaine
campaign, "the present generation of
drug habitues is hopeless. If I had my
way I would put them all in asylums
where I would keep them till they died.
Very few of them ever get cured of the
habit. While under restraint they can
do witnout their dope; but remove the
restraint and back to it they po, as fast
as they can get it."
I saw the record of another distress
ing case where the tragedy had been
carried farther. It was a Chicago wo
man, well born, an astist and musician,
who somehow acquired the cocaine
habit, and used to buy the drug from a
Chinaman. When this Chinaman was
tried for selling "coke" she testified as
follows: "I went to Hing's laundry and
asked for cocaine. I would have sold
my soul for the drug, but I had no
money and Hing had no pity. 'You
bring me money or jewelry, and I give
you coke,' he said. I went home. I
had given Hing my muffler, my pocket
book, my clock, my wedding ring, the
earrings my husband had given me, my
best Sunday dress. I had stripped my
home of everything. I had nothing left
and was dying for cocaine.
"Baby was playing on the floor when
I reached home. I saw the glitter of a
gold locket and chain about her neck.
I had scrimped and saved to buy this
trinket to make her happy. It was my
only hope. I snatched it from baby's
throat and ran back to the Chinaman
and he gave me cocaine."
There is a great difference between
cocaine and morphine. The morphine
habit is bad enough, but cocaine is in
finitely worse. The effects of one doic
of morphine last for many hours, often
for twenty-four; but the effects of oi.e
dose of cocaine cease within a single
hour —so another do?e must be taken,
and another and another. A man may
take morphine for 20 years or more and
do his work; but the slave to cocaine
does no work and rarely lives more than
five years.
"Coke fiends" have no desire for
food. They frequently go days without
eating and become gaunt and emaciat
ed. They pass many nights without
sleeping; in fact they cannot sleep till
they fall into a stupor of utter exhaustin.
Out of this stupor they come back to
consciousness with only one thought
and one fierce desire —to get more co
caine; they must get it to relieve their
intolerable suffering and craving, and
they are ready to get it by any possible
means. They will break any law, they
will commit any crime to get this drug
or to get money to buy it. It takes a
great deal more money to buy enough
cocaine to satisfy a coke fiend than it
takes to buy enough alcohol or opium
to satisfy the victims of those habits.
So the cocaine habit has formidable
importance in our cities in that it leads
directly and inevitably to crime. This
is true not only of victims in the under
world and the sporting world, where the
use of cocaine prevails extensively, but
also in the upper world, the professional
world where it also prevails to a disqui
eting extent.
A Chicago woman, Annie C. Meyers,
once well connected socially, in fact
she was one of the board of managers
of the Columbian exposition, became a
slave to the cocaine habit, and in a re
markable confession tells of many crimes
she committed in order to obtain the
drug. She tells how she was arrested
in Detroit, Cleveland, St. Louis, Indi
anapolis, and recently in Chicago for
stealing things in department stores.
She had completely lost her moral sense.
"I had been driven to such a state
that I thought the world against me,
and made up my mind to fight the world,
to steal, kill and play confidence games.
I associated with the worst class of forg
ers, counterfeiters and confidence men.
I once went 22 miles from the city of
Chicago to rob a house. I first had to
kill the dog, which I did by Rough on
Rats, then entered the house and stole
81000 and escaped. At another time,
thinking I did not have enough cocaine
to last me until morning and having no
money, it also being too late to go into
the stores, I deliberately took a pair of
shears and pried loose a tooth which
was filled with gold. I then extracted
the tooth, smasked it up, and taking
it to the nearest pawnshop (the blood
streaming down my face and drenching
my clothes) where I sold it for 80 cents.
I would break the windows of a vacant
house and get in to keep from freezing,
so the money I would be obliged to pay
for a night's lodging might be saved
for cocaine. I invented what is known
as the cocaine dance, and would go to
the sporting houses and dance and a
collection would be taken up for me."
• •••*•
Even granting that those physicians
who advocate complete abolition of the
drug may be too radical, can there be
j any question, in the light of the in
| effectiveness of our laws and their en
forcement, that the present unrestricted
manufacture of cocaine does not make
for the public good?
The legitimate use of cocaine in
medicines —it is used almost exclusively
as a local anesthetic in surgery and den
tistry —is so limited, I am assured, that
20,000 ounces a year would supply all
justifiable needs of the country. Why
should not this small amount be man
ufactured as a federal monopoly in a
federal factory, from which this most
dangerous drug would be delivered only
to hospitals and reputable physicians
for specified uses? —Hampton's Maga
zine for May.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88086023/1908-11-23/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>COCAINE FIENDS
F
PAGE SIX.
1
CERTAIN M POUNDS HAVE
VERY iAN(iEKOl'S EFFECTS
Drugs sokl Ovrr Sxla Fountain Clus
ters Slid lo 1W Injurious Iliilittk'i
phin I'li.vMdmi Wrewling Wku
Problem HUoh Stvms to He Ou
Increase Greedy Merchants Are
Condemned.
Philadelphia. The growth of the
abuse of cocaine here as well as else
where has stirred many prominent
physicians to emphatic expressions on
the subject. Dr. Henry Beates, Jr., of
the state board of medical examiners,
declares that the evil is exceedingly
dangerous, and that the time has
come when strenuous measures should
be taken to check It.
A new phase of the matter, of most
serious import. Is the fact that substi
tutes for cocaine are now being sold
by some druggists to cocaine fiends
possessing virtually the same quali
ties as the drug Itself, and, conse
quently equally pernicious when abus
ed. A widely advertised compounded
wine, for which tonic qualities are
claimed, and a beverage which Is sold
over soda fountain counters as an
innocent stimulant and nerve tonic
are said to contain one of these sub
stitutes. The substitutes for cocaine are
made by w hat is known as a synthetic
jiocess in other words, by combina
tion Cocaine itself as a laboratory
product bears the complex and sug
gestive name of menthylbenzolzonine.
Some of the substitutes are scientifi
cally known by even longer designa
tions. Sordid Desire of Gain.
The sordid desire of gain has led
to the placing of these on sale in va
rious forms which do not fall under
the prohibitive provisions of the anti-cocaine
act. One of the leading
analytical chemists said yesterday
that It would be neither wise nor hu
mane to publish a list of the substan
ces that possesses the qualities of co
caine, as this would be catering to the
vice of those who are suffering from
the cocaine habit. It is probable that
an effort -will be made to induce the
next legislature to prohibit also the
sale of these drugs without the pre
scription of a physician.
The discovery of the stimulating
action of cocaine is due to the prac
tice of the natives of Peru and other
South American countries of eating
the leaves of a certain shrub when
obliged to go without food for a long
time or to sustain unusual fatigue,
The effect Is to stimulate the nerves
and to postpone hunger. The active
principle of cocaine, in the form of
crystals, derived from the shrub, was
first Isolated In 1S55 by Gardeke, but
its important and peculiar properties
were not well understood until iss,
when Koller demonstrated to the
world Its wonderful power of produc
ing local loss of sensation. While It
has Important medical uses in isolat
ed cases, as in the production of suf
ficient loss of sensation when inject
ed Into the spinal canal to permit
of the amputation of a leg without
pain, it -was very soon found by phy
sicians that its continued use must be
avoided, as there was great danger
of forming a -habit much more diffi
cult to cure than even the use of mor
phine, DiStive Di-order.
When too much of the drug is tak
en disorders of the digestion quickly
appear, insomnia is extreme and ema
ciation and dropsy develop. The en
ft-eblement of the intellectual facul
ties is most marked, and an uncer
tain step, general apathy, sunken eyes
trembling lips and fetid breath mark
the habitual victim. The exhileration
reported from the use of the drug Is
not so great as many suppose, and its
duration is comparatively short.
Dr. Henry W. Cattell has made a
careful study of cocaine and Its ef
fect. "The habitual user of cocaine," he
said, "may be rightly termed a fiend,
the word In Anglo-Saxon meaning
enemy, because he actually becomes
an enemy to society. He steals, lies
and cheats; he develops a suicidal
tendency, and he becomes excessive
ly quarrelsome, and thus liable to
commit violence. The habit tightens
its grip upon a person in a compara
tively short time, and is hard to
shake off. If persisted in, it will
lead to insanity. The intervals be
tween the periods of exaltation pro-l
dueed by the drug are marked by deep
depression and a high state of ner
vous excitability.
"It was largely because of their
hope of extirpating this vice that
physicians took so great an Interest
In the passage of the pure food law
by congress. Additional legislation
is necessary to prevent the indiscrlm
nate wle of (ubstltutes for cocaine,
which are equally dangerous." </text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn2008060406/1913-03-28/ed-1/seq-11/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The Milwaukeeites roll their eyes to heaven like a
sick guinea and declare that if they prohibit this booz
ing business the people will all go to hitting the pipe,
taking cocaine and all these horrid things.
But right now the people up there are in the very
midst of an attempt to stamp out the cocaine habit,
which has grown up under the nourishing care of the
license system. The Oshkosh Northwestern describes
the situation thus:
An anti-cocaine crusade which has been launched in Mil
waukee has developed some rather startling disclosures at the
very start. More than two scores of boys and young men
summoned before the district attorney admitted they were
users of the deadly drug, and also implicated many others.
Some of the lads were mere schoolboys, belonging to re
spectable and well-to-do families, and. according to their
stories the use of cocaine is becoming increasingly common
among their associates. Not only boys are using the drug,
moreover, but girls are also addicted to the habit. And a
very important and significant lead was developed by the
claim that “agents” frequently “work” the public dance halls,
picking out likely victims and inducing them to try cocaine,
thereby starting fresh habitual users on the downward path.
American Issue humbly asks Milwaukee why it is
that if “Prohibition don’t prohibit,” they are making
all this hullaballoo about a little bit of cocaine.
And if the cocaine habit is a thing peculiar to dry
localities, what is the cause of this deplorable mess in
Milwaukee, where there are 2,000 saloons?
If Milwaukee had less beer and more brains, she
might be able to figure something out of this situation.
How dreadful it is for a municipality to have
neither brains to think nor eyes to see —nothing but
a mouth to drink.
</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85059732/1915-05-23/ed-1/seq-25/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE COFKTS.
In several courts men and wom
en found guilty of selling cocaine
have been given six months in jail,
while under the state laws they re
ceived no more than a $50 fine for
their offense. The $50 was paid by
the politician or drug vender and
all was over as far as the courts
were concerned, although the per
son arrested?man or woman?was
beaten almost into insensibility by
the drug-vender and other friends
when he or she returned to the
colony.
The terrible stress under which
these people live?where they.al
most worship the one man who can
supply them with drugs and are
cruelly beaten by him when they
are caught by private investigators
?has been revealed to Federal in
vestigators in recent raids. In fact.
It is the intention of the United
States government to go more deep
ly into these matters and ferret out
not the -poor unfortunates who sell
cocaine for commission of the
drug itself, but the real persons
who make the profit.
The Federal courts are meting
out jail sentences to the small of
fenders. but when the internal rev
enue agents get to the real sellers
of cocaine?the men who make a ?
great profit from the misfortunes of
their brothers?there will be sen
tences of not less than five years
in the Federal penitentiary, it Is
said.
The smaller offenders are the men
and women ?who sell the drug for
their master, the man in control of
the supply, for a commission on
drugs. They work and slave for
him and he owns rhom body and
soul by his payment of a small box
of cocaine or a few morphine tab
lets. The man in control is all the
more heartless in that he is not a
user of the drugs himself, (such a
man might be in sympathy -with oth
er stricken creatures) but is wise
enough to let It alone and profit by
their experiences.
In a recent raid of opium Joints
and lairs of the users of morphine
and cocaine. CoL L. G. XnttJto
charge of the eastern division, of
Missouri and one .of lie most eifi- .
A TYPICAL ALLEY WHERE "DOPE. r?END5'! TiHRUVE.
cient and experienced internal rev
enue agents in tie country, found
hundreds of unfortunates under' the
influence of drugs.
A CASE
IX POIXT.
In St. Louis his men under his di
rection arrested Henry "Wilsman.
the so-called "Cocaine King." This
man. known as "Big Henry." and
having ierved a penitentiary sen
tence icr slaying "Red" Tremaine.
the lasy "cocaine king," is alleged to
have T/een selling the drugs to a
colony of cocaine and morphine
users in a miserable row of tene
ments nearby?a structure known as
Filipino Row. and so filthy and foul
that no human being, unless under
the influence of drugs, would live
there. She lives la a
basement hovel of one of her own
buildings and is In fear of the death
that she knows the cocaine-nends
will mete out to her some day. She
has money and she thinks that some
night some maddened drug user will
come to her miserable dwelling ana
murder her for her money.
-In all of the misery and filth that
surround her; she is not more mis
erable than .the unfortunates who
pay-her for the rent of their squalid
one-room dwellings, and pay glad
' ly so that thev may be near their,
source of supply of the drugs. er energy then, excited
under the influence of drugs, was at
such a pitch that she easily could
earn enough money for tomorrow's
cocaine.
She and others lived this same life
day after day?working far into the'
?wight to buy. cocaine and then
spending the greater part of the day
in recovering from its-effects.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88065202/1905-11-09/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>WILD SCOPE OF COCAINE HA3IT
The Present Law in Maryland is Said
to Be Inadequate.
In spite of the law passed by the
(last Legislature governing the sale
( of cocaine, it is very probable that
: further action will be taken this
: fall to curb the constantly growing
; evil of "coke" taking, which is
- mining the lives of thousands of
persons, both white and colored,
’in Maryland. The facility with
which the drug can be purchased
and applied to the human consti
tution, as well as its terrible hold
upon the system, and the awful
life of suffering to which it ulti
mately leads makes cocaine, in the
eyes of medical men, a danger one
hundred fold greater than the
menace of the liquor traffic.
Dr. George L. Wilkins, the
physician to the Baltimore city
jail, said that the law is absolutely
of no avail in prohibiting the sale,
as proven by' the cases of cocaine
friends which come under his care
at the jail every year.
‘‘There has been absolutely no
lessening of the evil,” said Dr.
| Wilkins, ‘‘and some druggists are
selling cocaine as openly as ever.
I consider it a disgrace to the state
of Maryland that it seems to be
doing nothing to break up the indis
criminating sale of the drug: there
should certainly be passed some
drastic form of law which will sure
ly and effectively break up the
evil. I know absolutely, from the
word of patients who came before
me in the jail, that the stuff is
sold openly by some druggists who
are willing to thus make money
by wrecking the lives of their fel
low-creatures. I cannot say that
there has been any increase in the
number of cocaine patients since
the passage of the law, but there
is certainly no diminution in their
number. “The use of cocaine as a habit
1 is on the increase right here in
Baltimore, and I know what I am
talking about.
“Is it sold surreptitiously? Well,
no it is not necessary to do that;
some drug stores simply sell it
openly. Why, a man can get all
the cocaine he wants right now in
Baltimore from any druggist.
There is a law against selling co
caine, but the law is constantly be
ing violated. There seems to be
no more trouble in purchasing co- j
caiue in any form or quantity than
there is in buying soda water. The
chief trouble which the authorities
are encountering is the difficulty
of proving the sale on the part of
the druggists. But they have in
disputable evidence that the law
is being violated every day. “The cocaine fiend himself ham
' pers the authorities in every possi
ble way in trying to enforce a law
which he knows will deprive him
of the drug.
"In that respect he differs from
the victims of other ‘habits’ which
tend to run down society. He
will not divulge under any circum
stances, the source of his drug sup
ply, and the men who deal in it
sell with the assurance that their
lawbreaking will not be divulged.
I could not begin to define the
class of men and women who are
addicted to the use of cocaine in
its various forms," continued Mr.
Stillman. “The list runs from the
professional man and society wo
man down to the dregs of the
slums. In many instances its use
is begun innocently, and I believe
that many take the drug through
j prescriptions given by doctors and
| never know what they are taking
even when the habit has grown
well upon them. I have known
such cases.”
In Maryland and other Southern
states the hold which cocaine has
upon the negroes is terrible. The
practice of snuffing the drug was
introduced by the negros of the
South, who, in some way, got to
using it. Undoubtedly, they were
given to the practice of inhailing
through the nostrils by their pov
erty, which forbade the ownership
of a hypodermic syringe and the
additional cost of the liquid solu
tion of the drug.
Formerly the habit existed only
among the city negroes, but it has
now reached the country districts,
and the demoralization which it
has caused there is largely respon
sible for them leaving the country
and flocking to the cities, leaving
the farms without hands lo work
them.
The last days of a cocaine fiend
are something too horrible for
tongue to describe.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84022472/1909-06-14/ed-1/seq-10/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Every effort is being made to
enforce the new state law against the
sale of excessive quantities of this
drug for the uses of the "dope fiend"
rather than the doctor. Fully 75 per
cent, of the cocaine that passes
through this city, the police admit,
finds its way to the victims of the
deadly drug through an underground
system, of traffic which draws princi
pally from foreign sources.
With no duty upon cocoa leaves,
from which illicit purveyors extract a
rough form of cocaine for their drug
crazed customers, and only a low tar
iff imposed upon the quantities of "the
drug that are shipped here for secret
distribution throughout the country, it
is recognized that the chances for con
trolling the spreading cocaine curse
are to-day very slim, even under the
most strict state laws and police sur
veillance. Urging the recent recom
mendation of the American Health
League for "a prohibitory tariff, in
ternal revenue tax and other means
which will restrict the use of cocaine,
its substitutes and derivatives, to med
ical purposes," members of the medi
cal profession, welfare workers, cler
gymen and the leading drug houses
here are now looking to Congress to
safeguard every community in the
country by thus shutting off this chief
source of the illegal supply of the nox
ious drug. Though restrictive laws
can be and are being successfully en
forced by compelling the local manu
facturers and wholesalers to keep re
cords of their cocaine sale's, it has
been provan, unscrupulous retailers to
whom the American houses refuse to
sell excessive quantities are perfect
ly free to obtain a limitless and un
traceable supply from abroad.
More cocaine is sold to drug vic
tims from one of their supply stations
in a single night than an ordinary
drug store could sell for medicinal
purposes in a year, the police de
clare. Medical men who are inter
esting themselves in urging congress
to give the homes of this country
this high tariff protection from the
ravages of the drug assert that the
comparatively small supply of cocaine
necessary for professionai purpose
will still be readily available for their
uses. With a tariff of $1.50 an ounce
put upon the foreign cocaine sup
ply and a duty of five cents on each
pounds Of cocoa leaves it is proposed
to decisively check the cocaine plague
and place it flnmly unto govern
ment Control by an internal revenue
tax.
No power but that of the people
can now induce the law makers at
Washington to include in the Aldrich
Payne bill this necessary clause for
the protection of every American
family, the leaders in this movement
declared today. If every philanthrop
ic, medical and charitable organiza
tion throughout the land will recom
mend to its members an immediate ap
peal to Senator Lodge, who is pre
senting this matter, or to their re
presentatives in congress, it is be
lieved these effiorts to combat the
curse of cocaine may succeed.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84025828/1898-01-22/ed-1/seq-3</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Cocaine Is mailo
from cocn leaves, nnd tlio main coun
try fUipplyliiR these leaves Is 1'eru.
It Is dllttcult to divide thu remark
able Increase In the use of cocaine Into
legitimate or medical use nnd Illegiti
mate use by victims of the cocaine
habit. Hut It Is certain that the In
crease of J00 per cent. In three years Is
by no means wholly legitimate.
There nro many physicians who will
not use morphine or nny dangerous
drug to alleviate n recurring pain. One
of thu foremost specialists In nervous
diseases In New York says Hint for
years ho knew of other doctors who
took similar ground. Neither would he
uso cocnluo for neuralgia. There nro
other drugs, he said, which give relief,
without the danger of fastening uimiii
the pntleiit n habit which could not bo
shaken off. Even If thesu drugs are
not taken ns n stimulant, their con
stant use requires larger nnd larger
quantities to reduce thu pain. Ah a
local anaesthetic cocaine Is valuable,
but not Invaluable. In surgical cases
It Is extremely useful In making nny
part insensible to pain. Thu effect Is
purely local, however, and never can
result In the formation of a habit.
Said a member of thu faculty of the
College of Pharmacy tlio other day: "I
belluvu the cocaliiu habit Is growing
last. Terrible as Is thu morphine habit,
thu cocaluu habit Is even worse, be
cause It lead quickly and Inevitably to
Insanity, from which no olio can re
cover. "It Is not n boy's habit, this taking of
cocaine. There aru plenty of boy opium
smokers, and no end of women to keep
them company. Hut the victims of co
caine aru usually In thu prime of life,
from .'to to -10 years old. Tliey may
have l.een Introduced to thu drug by
thu family physician, who has advised
Its uso for thu relief of neuralgia, or
who lias used It In spray In throat and
nose troubles, or the dentist may have
made operations upon the teeth pain
less by cocaine, or, again, In thu vari
ous preparations of coca and kola wines
they may havu had their llrst taste.
These wines hardly could hurt If thu
uso of cocaluu stopped there. Hut
many times It does not. After n -while
the exhilaration and good feeling due
to the wine docs not come. Some
thing stronger is needed. Then comes
thu cocaine, puru nnd simple. Once
In thu clureli of thu drug, not one In it
thousand breaks away.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1925-10-28/ed-1/seq-10/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>David
f\ Winebrenner and Harry S. Snook
of Frederick. Md., were held for trial
in $5,000 bail on charge of purchase
anil possession of cocaine and I)r. J. J.
Kensberg of Mount IMensant, Md., was
held in SI,OOO bail for the alleged il
legal sale off cocaine late yesterday by
Failed States Commissioner .1. Frank
Supplee. after a preliminary hearing j
on a charge of conspiracy to violate i
the Harrison narcotic act.
Boyd M. Martin, head of the nar
cotic agents in Baltimore for 10 years, 1
was 11 io chief witness against the ac
cused. He told how his suspicions
were aroused when an inspection of
Dr. Kensborg's records showed large
purchases of cocaine.
Martin asked Konsberp for an ex- |
planation. “I'm sorry, but I can't tell;
you,” the doctor replied, according to j
Martin. *
"It would involve some of the most '
prominent people in Frederick County i
mid shake this whole section of the
Mate.”
Martin testified Kensberg told him
later the man he let have the cocaine
tvas Winebrenner. When asked what
arrangements lie had with Wine
brenner, Kensberg said Winebrenner
came to his office last December and
wanted him to sell some cocaine, the !
agent said.
Martin then testified that he ar- |
ranged with Rensbut-g to place an or- j
der to trap Winebrenner and Snook, j
On October 5. lie said, Kensberg re
ceived from a Bristol (Tenn.) drug
house 24 bottles of cocaine and 1 bot
tle of morphine. It was sent by liar-'
cel post C. O. I). and cost 842.05. ]
Three days later, he said, Snook and
‘Winebrenner drove tip to Rensberg’s I
office and Snook went in and got the j
drugs, paying sl4'.'.
Martin and another agent grabbed
him as he came out, took him back,
and Snook, protesting, according to
Martin, that he was a gentleman and
should not be searched, produced the
£4 bottles of cocaine.</text>
	  </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn87065612/1907-02-01/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Cocaine, the Agent of Hell.
That the blind tiger evil is one that in
a great menace to this State, no oh e
will deny, but tho cocaine habit, while
perhaps not so extensive, is far worse.
In speaking of this evil, Judge Wilkin
son, In a recent charge to tfce grand
jury, said he regarded tho cocaine hab
it as one of tho most dangerous with
which the law has to combat, and de
nounced the seller of it as a “knot on
nature and a scab on humanity.” It
crazes and perverts their perceptive
faculties so that they “see men like
stumps, horses like people, and trees
like angels.”
The negro brute who a few days ago
at Greenville shot eleven people and
killed four or ffve of them before he
could be arested, was no victim
of the cocaine habit. The illegal sale
of cocaine, as well as whiskey, ought to
be made a penitentiary offense, in order
that It might be suppressed.
Under the above caption, the Aber
deen Examiner timely remarks:
Tho Aberdeen Examiner was the first
i paper in America to war against the
indiscriminate sale of cocaine and to
appeal for legislation prohibiting Its
sale except on medical certificate. Fall
ing to secure consideration from our leg
islature, we kept up the fight until gen
erally reinforced by the press, and Ark
ansas passed the first restrictive law;
Mississippi followed and one by one the
Northern mining and manufacturing
States are falling In line. But is the
law being generally enforced? So far
as our observation goes, and we read all
published charges, our judges are not
impressing grand juries with the im
portance of this fulraination against tho
most awful of all crime-breeding agen
cies. With the introduction of cocaine
there dawned upon the South an era of
negro demoralization and crime, that
has kept pace with thp con
sumption of the hellish drug, and the
monster, as fn the North, is making
constant inroads now upon the white
population, and opening anew field of
venal enterprise to peddiors of both
races. Unless this vile trade is arres
ted, the negro population will be moral-,
lv and physically ruined and the white
race degiadcd. Many of our judges and
reformers berate crime, but they do not
strike at the chief modern agency, an
agency a thousand times more potent,
masterful and fearful than alcohol, and
in many cases substituted for it. Tho
next legislature, in the interest of hu
manity, peace and morality, an/i as a
barrier against crimes of the basest
character, must prohibit by heavy pen
alties tho sale of this terrible drug to
any one but a licensed physician or sur_
geon, such sales to be made direct. Our
local druggists are observing the exist
ing law. Colored preachers are doing
their utmost to combat this evil, and to
these influencies is due the exemption
of this country from certain character
of crime that has coursed other commu
nities.</text>
	  </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
